<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Design Patterns | (think)]]></title>
  <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/categories/design-patterns/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://batsov.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-06-16T17:27:48+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://batsov.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bozhidar Batsov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The best way to implement the Singleton pattern in Java and Ruby]]></title>
    <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/2008/09/29/singleton-java-ruby/"/>
    <updated>2008-09-29T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://batsov.com/articles/2008/09/29/singleton-java-ruby</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I haven’t posted anything lately, but I just received my brand new
<strong>Das Keyboard</strong> and now I simply can’t stop typing. Recently I’ve been
going through some effective technics to implement popular design
patterns and I was surprised to see how few people where aware of
them. For example since Java 5 the best way to implement the Singleton
pattern is simply to use an enum like this:</p>

<p>``` java
public enum SomeClass {</p>

<pre><code>INSTANCE;
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>This is possible due to the fact that in Java(unlike in C++ and C#)
enums are full-blown classes(although they do not support features
like inheritance for example). You get an added bonus when using an
enum class – you do not have to worry about serialization – this is
handled for you behind the scenes.</p>

<p>And this is how one should implement the Singleton pattern in Ruby:</p>

<p>``` ruby
require &lsquo;singleton&rsquo;</p>

<p>class Some
  include Singleton
end
```</p>

<p>Through the magic of Ruby’s mix-ins you get a private constructor for
your class and an instance method with which you can obtain a
reference to the single instance of the class. And best of all –
because this library has undergone a substantial degree of testing it
is pretty much bulletproof. Things hardly get simpler than that.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
