<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Debian | (think)]]></title>
  <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/categories/debian/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://batsov.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-15T11:05:28+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://batsov.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bozhidar Batsov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Debian post installation setup & tips]]></title>
    <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/2011/07/04/debian-tips/"/>
    <updated>2011-07-04T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://batsov.com/articles/2011/07/04/debian-tips</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Prelude</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve recently been using Debian a lot (mostly Debian Wheezy (aka
testing)), So I&rsquo;ve decided to adapt my
<a href="/Linux/Fedora/2011/05/31/fedora-15-tips.html">Fedora 15 post installation setup &amp; tips</a>
article for Debian. Here are some of the common things I add to a
typical &ldquo;graphical desktop&rdquo; Debian installation as well as some tips
and tricks that you&rsquo;ll hopefully find useful. Btw, I highly recommend
you to use the <a href="http://cdimage.debian.org/cdimage/daily-builds/daily/arch-latest/amd64/iso-cd/debian-testing-amd64-netinst.iso">netinstall Debian distribution</a> &ndash; that way you&rsquo;ll get an
up-to-date installation immediately and you won&rsquo;t have to download
huge installation images.</p>

<p>This article will be of use mostly to people using Debian as a desktop
OS (with GNOME as their desktop environment) &ndash; it doesn&rsquo;t discuss any
server configurations.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Tweak defaults</h2>

<h4>Configure sudo</h4>

<p><code>sudo</code> gives you a way to execute single commands as the superuser. You
can also do this with <code>su -c</code>, but you have to quote the commands there,
which I don&rsquo;t like very much. To enable sudo for some account first
run the command:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ su -c "visudo"
</code></p>

<p>The file <code>/etc/sudoers</code> will open up in a customized vi editor. Append
somewhere to the end of the file the following line:</p>

<p><code>username ALL=(ALL) ALL</code></p>

<p>You should replace <em>username</em> with your username.</p>

<h2>apt-get + apt-cache or aptitude</h2>

<p>There are two common ways (and many others less popular or obsolete)
to manage packages on a Debian system these days &ndash; the simpler <code>apt-get</code>
+ <code>apt-cache</code> combo or the more advanced <code>aptitude</code> tool. I tend to prefer
using aptitude since it&rsquo;s a all-in-one solution &ndash; you could use it to both
query and install packages and has both a CLI and a curses interface.</p>

<p>It doesn&rsquo;t really matter whether you decided to use apt-get/apt-cache
or aptitude, but you shouldn&rsquo;t mix their usage &ndash; pick one and stay
with it.</p>

<h2>Install additional software</h2>

<p>I generally install Debian from the netinstall images and don&rsquo;t
customize very much the default package set since it&rsquo;s so easy to
install everything you need afterwards.</p>

<h4>Install REAL text editors</h4>

<p>gedit is ok for causal text editing, but professionals like software
engineers and system administrators will definitely need something more:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install emacs vim
</code></p>

<p>Personally I use Emacs most of the time and use vim only to edit
config files that require root access. If you need an advanced Emacs
setup my suggestion is the <a href="https://github.com/bbatsov/emacs-dev-kit">Emacs Dev Kit</a>.</p>

<h4>Install Z Shell</h4>

<p>It&rsquo;s no secret that I love the Z Shell &ndash; after all I
<a href="/Z%20Shell/2011/04/29/one-shell-to-rule-them-all.html">rave about it</a>
quite often. It should come as no surprise that I happen to use it and
probably you should start using it as well:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install zsh
$ sudo vim /etc/passwd
</code></p>

<p>Find the line about your account and change there <code>/bin/bash</code> to
<code>/usr/bin/zsh</code>. Alternatively you can use the chsh program to
achieve the same result:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo chsh
</code></p>

<p>Afterwards start a new login shell and a simple wizard will
fire up asking you some questions to create a default .zshrc file for
you. Alternatively you can use the excellent <a href="https://github.com/robbyrussell/oh-my-zsh">O My Zsh</a> config &ndash; I&rsquo;m
very fond of it.</p>

<h4>Install guake(a drop down terminal)</h4>

<p>I spend a lot of time at the terminal and like to have one at my
fingertips always. Since I&rsquo;m a GNOME user guake is the best option for
me:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install guake
</code></p>

<h4>Install LibreOffice</h4>

<p>LibreOffice is currently the best Linux option for word processing,
spreadsheet handling and presentation creation. It&rsquo;s generally
installed by default if you select the &ldquo;Graphical Desktop&rdquo; option in
the installation wizard, but you can install the
most common components at any time with the following command:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install libreoffice-calc libreoffice-impress libreoffice-draw libreoffice-writer
</code></p>

<p>LibreOffice uses hunspell to do spellchecking. An English dictionary
will be installed by default, but you&rsquo;ll need to install additional
dictionaries manually:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install hunspell-bg
</code></p>

<p>This command will install the Bulgarian hunspell dictionary. You
likely don&rsquo;t need it so install some more helpful dictionary instead. :&ndash;)</p>

<h4>Install OpenJDK</h4>

<p>If you need to run Java programs/applets:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install openjdk-6-jre
</code></p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re planning to do some Java development:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install openjdk-6-jdk openjdk-6-doc openjdk-6-demo openjdk-6-source
</code></p>

<h4>Install Deluge torrent client</h4>

<p>The default Transmission torrent client is pretty basic. I recommend
you to replace it with the much more feature-rich deluge:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install deluge
</code></p>

<h4>Install Inconsolata font</h4>

<p>I&rsquo;m a software engineer and I obviously spend a lot of time reading
and writing source code. I&rsquo;m very picking about the monospace font
that I use and currently Inconsolata happens to be my favorite:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install ttf-inconsolata
</code></p>

<h4>Install GIMP</h4>

<p>A lot of you might need an image editor. GIMP is generally
considered the best option so you might want to install it:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install gimp
</code></p>

<h2>Install additional patent encumbered/proprietary software</h2>

<h4>Enable non-free repo</h4>

<p>Just add contrib and non-free to the list of your enabled repos. Your
first line in /etc/apt/sources.list should look like this:</p>

<p><code>bash
deb http://ftp.bg.debian.org/debian/ wheezy main contrib non-free
</code></p>

<p>Then do a:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude update
</code></p>

<h4>Install proprietary codecs</h4>

<p>No MP3 support in Debian by default? And almost no video codecs?
Non-free to the rescue! Type this:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install gstreamer-plugins-ugly gstreamer-plugins-bad gstreamer-ffmpeg
</code></p>

<h4>Install VLC</h4>

<p>With MPlayer&rsquo;s development in stagnation VLC has established itself as
the best video player for Linux recently. Installing it is as easy as typing the following command:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install vlc
</code></p>

<h4>Install Adobe Flash Player</h4>

<p>Love it or hate it &ndash; you probably need it.</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install flashplugin-nonfree
</code></p>

<p>You can omit this if you&rsquo;re planning to use Google Chrome (on a 32bit system), since it
comes with Flash Player built-in.</p>

<h4>Install Skype</h4>

<p>In a perfect world everyone would be using Google Talk&hellip; In the real one:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install skype
</code></p>

<h4>Install Oracle JDK</h4>

<p>OpenJDK is great, but due to licensing problems it&rsquo;s not quite the
same as the Oracle JDK. If you start experiencing strange problems
(mostly in Swing programs) you&rsquo;d probably do well to try the Oracle
JDK instead. The magic incantation goes like this:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install sun-java6-jdk sun-java6-demo sun-java6-source sun-java6-plugin
</code></p>

<p>Debian uses OpenJDK by default, so you&rsquo;ll have to do some more work to
tell it to start using Oracle JDK. The <code>alternatives</code> program allows
you to select between multiple installed versions of a program:</p>

<p>These commands will make alternative aware of the java binaries and
set high priorities to them which will make them the default Java
binaries. You can use &ldquo;alternatives &mdash;config binaryname&rdquo; to select
active binaries manually.</p>

<h4>Install Google Chrome</h4>

<p>Firefox is dying, Google Chrome is the new king of the
browsers. Download it from the <a href="http://www.google.com/chrome">official site</a> and install it:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo dpk -i ~/Downloads/google-chrome-stable_current_i386.deb
</code></p>

<p>Google Chrome will install a apt repository as well, so you&rsquo;ll receive
updates as soon as they arrive.</p>

<p>Alternatively you can use Chromium &ndash; Chrome&rsquo;s open source sibling:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install chromium-browser
</code></p>

<h4>Install DropBox</h4>

<p><a href="http://www.dropbox.com">DropBox</a> is a great file sharing service
which allows you to sync files between all of your computers and
mobile devices(Android, iPhone, iPad, etc). It has a great Linux
client which I use all the time. It&rsquo;s available in the non-free repo
so you can install it like this:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo aptitude install nautilus-dropbox
</code></p>

<h2>Epilogue</h2>

<p>Hopefully some of my setup has made your setup more enjoyable and more
productive. I&rsquo;ll update this article along the way if I stumble upon
other things that I consider to be generally helpful.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
