<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Hardware | (think)]]></title>
  <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/categories/hardware/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://batsov.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-15T11:05:28+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://batsov.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bozhidar Batsov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Running Xerox Phaser 3117 under Fedora 15]]></title>
    <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/2011/06/04/phaser-3117-fedora-15/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-04T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://batsov.com/articles/2011/06/04/phaser-3117-fedora-15</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been a GNU/Linux user for quite some time now and a Fedora user
for just as long. The first distribution that I ever used was Fedora 2
and even though I&rsquo;ve used extensively other distros I&rsquo;ve always come
back to Fedora. Recently Fedora 15 was released and I was
(naturally) one of the first people to install it.</p>

<p>Everything is great in the new release (as ever), but my Xerox Phaser
3117 printer is unsupported (also as ever) out of the box, so it&rsquo;s
time for one of those quick articles on how to get it up and running this
time. First run the following command as root (or with sudo):</p>

<p>``` bash</p>

<h1>yum install gutenprint-foomatic</h1>

<p>```</p>

<p>Now you can run the &ldquo;Printing&rdquo; application. It will autodetect your
printer and suggest you to use the driver for Xerox Phaser 3110. Just
accept this suggestion and you should be good to go. Happy printing!</p>

<p>P.S. You might also want to check out my article on
<a href="/Linux/Fedora/2011/05/31/fedora-15-tips.html">Fedora 15 post installation setup</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Enabling 3D support for Nouveau in Fedora 13]]></title>
    <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/2010/05/26/3d-support-nouveau-fedora-13/"/>
    <updated>2010-05-26T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://batsov.com/articles/2010/05/26/3d-support-nouveau-fedora-13</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Most of you probably have heard that Fedora 13 will feature
experimental 3D support for the Nouveau open source driver for Nvidia
cards. This support, however, is not enabled by default. To enable it
you need to install the mesa-dri-drivers-experimental package. I,
personally, do it like this(if you haven’t configured sudo, you’ll
have to perform this as root):</p>

<p><code>bash
sudo yum install mesa-dri-drivers-experimental
</code></p>

<p>Afterwards you can enable Compuz, play chromium-bsu or whatever your heart desires.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using Xerox Phaser 3117 on Fedora]]></title>
    <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/2009/09/25/xerox-phaser-3117-fedora/"/>
    <updated>2009-09-25T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://batsov.com/articles/2009/09/25/xerox-phaser-3117-fedora</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The driver selected by default by Fedora 11 is not appropriate for
Xerox Phaser 3117 &ndash; it will not print with it. However there is a very
easy solution to the problem.</p>

<p>Go to <strong>System &ndash;> Administration &ndash;> Printing</strong> (In GNOME at least, in KDE
it’s probably something similar). Right click the Xerox Phaser 3117
printer icon there and select &ldquo;Properties&rdquo; from the menu. Then in the
&ldquo;Make and model&rdquo; section choose change and then select Samsung
ML-1710.</p>

<p>After you apply the change you&rsquo;ve just made, you can start printing
with your Phaser.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Das Keyboard]]></title>
    <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/2008/06/16/das-keyboard/"/>
    <updated>2008-06-16T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://batsov.com/articles/2008/06/16/das-keyboard</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Every professional developer knows how important to the development
process the keyboard is, so it is only natural to be on the look for
some quality piece of hardware. After a long research in the area of
good keyboards I decided to upgrade my current rig to the recently
released <a href="http://www.daskeyboard.com/">Das Keyboard 3</a>.</p>

<p><img class="mechanical_keyboard.jpg <a" src="href="http://www.daskeyboard.com/images/products/mechanical_keyboard.jpg">http://www.daskeyboard.com/images/products/mechanical_keyboard.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>Das Keyboard comes in three flavours &ndash; Professional(mechanical
keyboard with labelled keys), Ultimate(the original mechanical
keyboard with blank keys) and Silent(mechanical keyboard with labelled
keys that doesn&rsquo;t produce the trademarked clicking sound of the
original Das Keyboard).</p>

<p>I bought the Ultimate model, of course. I&rsquo;ve been a touch typist for
several years now and I didn&rsquo;t really cared about the labelled
keys(though I did miss them in games). Two words describe this
keyboard perfectly &ndash; <strong>Bad Ass</strong>. It&rsquo;s without a doubt the single
finest piece of keyboard hardware that I&rsquo;ve touched, it&rsquo;s very
comfortable, very solid and I feel that I&rsquo;ve actually improved my
typing speed with it. My colleagues don&rsquo;t like the noisy work of the
keyboard very much, but I have no problems with it. I actually have
grown quite fond of it.</p>

<p>The keyboard also features a two port USB hub, that I didn&rsquo;t really
consider when I was buying it, but it turned out quite helpful. I&rsquo;ve
actually stopped using the USB ports of my computer entirely(except
for input devices) &ndash; I use the keyboard hub to plug-in flash drives
and charge devices. When your computer is sitting beneath a desk you
learn to appreciate USB hubs very quickly.</p>

<p>I have long heard stories about Das Keyboard&rsquo;s quality
and comfort and I it has totally lived up to its hype. They price is
admittedly a bit steep(I bought two keyboards for home and for work
each costing 130$), but this is our hands and productivity we&rsquo;re
talking about so we shouldn&rsquo;t be cheap. So what are
waiting for &ndash; research the market yourselves and make your pick, your
hands deserve a quality keyboard(the Das Keyboard)!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
