<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: emacs | (think)]]></title>
  <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/categories/emacs/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://batsov.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-06-17T12:45:14+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://batsov.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bozhidar Batsov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CIDER 0.9]]></title>
    <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/2015/06/16/cider-0-dot-9/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-16T15:59:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://batsov.com/articles/2015/06/16/cider-0-dot-9</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://github.com/clojure-emacs/cider">CIDER</a> 0.9 is finally out and
it&rsquo;s our best release yet (believe it or not)! It took a lot
more time than I originally anticipated, but at least we managed to
ship in time for <a href="http://euroclojure.org">EuroClojure</a>!</p>

<p>There are a ton of important changes and new features in 0.9 and now I&rsquo;ll go
quickly through some of them.</p>

<h3>Debugger</h3>

<p>Believe it or not CIDER now has a debugger! This was like
the most requested feature ever, so I&rsquo;m sure at least some of you are
excited. The debugger was developed by the awesome
<a href="http://endlessparentheses.com">Artur Malabarba</a>. He even wrote
<a href="http://endlessparentheses.com/cider-debug-a-visual-interactive-debugger-for-clojure.html">a post about it</a>
and I guess you should read it.</p>

<h3>Dependency isolation</h3>

<p>CIDER&rsquo;s dependencies will no longer affect your projects (read this as
<em>introduce dependency conflicts in them</em>). All the dependencies are
now isolated using source rewriting (simply put &ndash; they live in
different namespaces than the original libraries). This magic is done by
<a href="https://github.com/benedekfazekas/mranderson">mranderson</a>. Thanks to
<a href="https://github.com/benedekfazekas">Benedek Fazekas</a> for creating this
small but super helpful tool!</p>

<h3>Rich code completion</h3>

<p>Completion candidates are now annotated with information about the
namespace and the type of the thing being completed. It&rsquo;s pretty neat.</p>

<p><img class="<a" src="href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/clojure-emacs/cider/master/screenshots/completion-annotations.png">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/clojure-emacs/cider/master/screenshots/completion-annotations.png</a>"></p>

<p>The screenshot above features
<a href="http://company-mode.github.io/">company-mode</a>. The annotations are
not supported in <code>auto-complete-mode</code> (that&rsquo;s a limitation of AC, not
a limitation of CIDER).</p>

<h3>Misc additions</h3>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a short list of other important additions:</p>

<ul>
<li>Support for Piggieback 0.2</li>
<li>New code formatting commands (based on <a href="https://github.com/weavejester/cljfmt">cljfmt</a>)</li>
<li>New EDN data formatting commands</li>
</ul>


<h2>Changes</h2>

<p>There were also a few important changes. Most notably we had to
<a href="https://github.com/clojure-emacs/cider/issues/1088">kill source-tracking code evaluation</a>,
as it wasn&rsquo;t playing nice with ClojureScript. This was also a hacky
solution and I still hope than one day this will be properly supported
in nREPL itself. In simple terms &ndash; var definitions evaluated by
themselves won&rsquo;t have any location metadata set for them, which will
make it impossible to go their definition.  You can also help out by
voicing your support for this
<a href="http://dev.clojure.org/jira/browse/NREPL-59">nREPL ticket</a>&rsquo;s patch to
be merged.</p>

<p>You&rsquo;ll also notice that some commands that didn&rsquo;t prompt for
confirmation in the past do so now (e.g. <code>find-var</code>).  This was done mostly for
consistency with Emacs&rsquo;s own commands that do similar things. The
behavior is configurable via <code>cider-prompt-for-symbol</code>. If a ton of
people dislike the new defaults reverting them is on the table.</p>

<h2>All the Gory Details</h2>

<p>There were truly a ton of changes and there&rsquo;s little point in me
repeating them here. If you want to know everything have a look at the
<a href="https://github.com/clojure-emacs/cider/releases/tag/v0.9.0">release notes</a>.</p>

<h2>The Road Ahead</h2>

<p>Going forward our top priority will be merging some functionality from
<a href="https://github.com/clojure-emacs/refactor-nrepl">refactor-nrepl</a> and
<a href="https://github.com/clojure-emacs/clj-refactor.el">clj-refactor</a> into
CIDER itself.  Think of things like <code>find-usages</code>,
<code>extract-definition</code>, etc. Refining the debugger will be another top
priority.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;ll also try to do some important internal changes:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/clojure-emacs/cider/issues/1068">reorganize the entire codebase in a more sensible manner</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/clojure-emacs/cider/issues/1099">rework nREPL response handling</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/clojure-emacs/cider/issues/709">rework the REPL to use <code>comint-mode</code></a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/clojure-emacs/cider/issues/732">improve quitting and restarting</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Depending of how well we progress on those tasks the next release will
be either 0.10 or 1.0. I won&rsquo;t make any commitments about its release
date (but judging from past it will likely be 3 to 6 months from now).</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re wondering why things are moving more slowly lately, here&rsquo;s
the answer for you &ndash; I&rsquo;ve been super busy since the beginning of the
year and haven&rsquo;t had much time for open-source projects. I&rsquo;m hoping
this will change, but only time will tell.  I&rsquo;m very happy that a lot
of people contributed to the development of CIDER 0.9. The project
definitely doesn&rsquo;t have a bus factor of one. :&ndash;)</p>

<p>Special thanks to <a href="https://github.com/cichli">Michael Griffiths</a> who
did a ton of great work on this release. You rock!</p>

<p><strong>P.S.</strong> Recently I talked on the
<a href="http://blog.cognitect.com/cognicast">Cognicast</a> about CIDER (in
general and 0.9 in particular). You might find
<a href="http://blog.cognitect.com/cognicast/080">this episode</a> interesting.</p>

<p><strong>P.P.S.</strong> I&rsquo;m rarely on IRC these days. <code>#cider</code> on
  <a href="https://clojurians.slack.com/">slack</a> and our
  <a href="https://gitter.im/clojure-emacs/cider">gitter channel</a> are the
  official CIDER chats as far as I&rsquo;m concerned.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A CIDER Unsession at Clojure/conj]]></title>
    <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/2014/11/15/a-cider-unsession-at-clojure-slash-conj/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-15T20:17:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://batsov.com/articles/2014/11/15/a-cider-unsession-at-clojure-slash-conj</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ll be talking about the evolution of CIDER at the
<a href="http://clojure-conj.org/">conj</a>, but I won&rsquo;t be able to show much (in
terms of features) during my talk. Luckily, however, beside the talks
we also have the option for <a href="https://github.com/cognitect/clojure-conj/wiki/Clojure-conj-2014-Unsessions">unsessions</a>. Here&rsquo;s my proposal for one such unsession&hellip;</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d like to do a more extensive demonstration of the general
workflow with CIDER and all the cool things we&rsquo;ve done recently and
I&rsquo;d also like discuss with our users (and potential users) existing
problems, ideas for improvements and the future direction of the
project. If you like my idea you can show your support for it
<a href="https://github.com/cognitect/clojure-conj/wiki/Clojure-conj-2014-Unsessions#cider-demoqa">here</a>.</p>

<p>Feedback is important and I&rsquo;d like to get as much as possible
to make CIDER better!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Profiling Extension for CIDER]]></title>
    <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/2014/11/15/a-profiling-extension-for-cider/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-15T20:16:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://batsov.com/articles/2014/11/15/a-profiling-extension-for-cider</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://github.com/edw">Edwin Watkeys</a> has just released a
<a href="https://github.com/thunknyc/nrepl-profile">profiling extension for CIDER</a>,
based on his library
<a href="http://github.com/thunknyc/profile">profile</a>. The profiling data you&rsquo;ll get
is rather crude, but it&rsquo;s still better than nothing and is certainly nicer
than what you&rsquo;d get by using <code>time</code>.</p>

<p>Here you can see the extension in action:</p>

<p><img class="<a" src="href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/636b6897b279bb761f3377f6e002bbdb8b474937/68747470733a2f2f7261772e6769746875622e636f6d2f7468756e6b6e79632f6e7265706c2d70726f66696c652f6d61737465722f646f632f70726f66696c652d73637265656e73686f742e706e67">https://camo.githubusercontent.com/636b6897b279bb761f3377f6e002bbdb8b474937/68747470733a2f2f7261772e6769746875622e636f6d2f7468756e6b6e79632f6e7265706c2d70726f66696c652f6d61737465722f646f632f70726f66696c652d73637265656e73686f742e706e67</a>"></p>

<p>Check out the documentation of both projects for more details.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Road to CIDER 0.8]]></title>
    <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/2014/11/10/the-road-to-cider-0-dot-8/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-10T15:27:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://batsov.com/articles/2014/11/10/the-road-to-cider-0-dot-8</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m planning to release the long overdue <a href="https://github.com/clojure-emacs/cider">CIDER</a> 0.8 at <a href="http://clojure-conj.org/">clojure/conj</a> 2014.
I&rsquo;ll be giving a talk there that will be mostly about CIDER, so this seems like a pretty good idea to me.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d like to ask you to do a bit of extra testing to the current
snapshot builds, so we can deliver a solid release (if we&rsquo;re lucky &ndash;
the most solid ever). Guess you should pay extra attention to the
<a href="https://github.com/clojure-emacs/cider/blob/master/CHANGELOG.md">new features</a>.</p>

<p>If you want to get some issue fixed in time for 0.8 you&rsquo;d better <a href="https://github.com/clojure-emacs/cider/issues">get started right away</a>.</p>

<p>Thanks in advance for your help!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CIDER 0.7]]></title>
    <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/2014/08/05/cider-0-dot-7/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-05T15:19:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://batsov.com/articles/2014/08/05/cider-0-dot-7</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://github.com/clojure-emacs/cider">CIDER</a> 0.7 is finally out and
it&rsquo;s an epic release! It&rsquo;s without a doubt the most important release
since the inception of the project about two years ago and it&rsquo;s the
biggest one in terms of features and code changes.</p>

<p>The release is special for a number of reasons. Allow me to quickly
enumerate though them.</p>

<h3>Middleware-based</h3>

<p>One of the huge problems we&rsquo;ve had so far was that a lot of
functionality that was present in SLIME + swank-clojure was missing in
CIDER. For many people the transition between the two didn&rsquo;t really
feel like an upgrade (although it was advertised as such) &ndash; after all
they lost things like inspection, tracing, apropos, caller cross-reference, the
debugger, etc.</p>

<p>The reason this happened was CIDER&rsquo;s initial approach of implementing
features by inlining Clojure code within the Emacs Lisp code and
evaluating this code in a dedicated nREPL session (called the tooling
session), to avoid contaminating the results in the &ldquo;primary&rdquo; eval
session. This approach had one upside (you didn&rsquo;t need any extra deps
(middleware) to run CIDER) and one huge downside (it&rsquo;s impossible
to maintain non-trivial inlined code; not to mention it&rsquo;s not very
practical). This meant that pretty much all third party libs were out
of the equation and pretty much every advanced feature.</p>

<p>This problem was initially address by
<a href="https://github.com/pallet/ritz">ritz</a>, which provided some extra
functionality built on top of extra nREPL middleware. As it was a
separate project it was hard to be kept in sync with the flurry of
changes in CIDER and was abandoned at some point. While <code>ritz</code> failed
it had the right approach and it served as the principle inspiration
for CIDER 0.7.</p>

<p>In CIDER 0.6 we introduced optional nREPL middleware for some
operations (like completion, error reporting, var info) and in 0.7 the
middleware stack was greatly extended, improved and promoted to a
mandatory CIDER component. This has one downside (you&rsquo;ll have to
install it to leverage all of CIDER&rsquo;s power) and a several upsides:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>A lot of the heavy lifting is now done in pure Clojure code (see
<a href="https://github.com/clojure-emacs/cider-nrepl">cider-nrepl</a>) and it&rsquo;s
much easier to implement complex features now (not to mention &ndash; this
code is much easier to maintain). This also means that it&rsquo;s much
easier for Clojure programmers to contribute to CIDER as a lot of
functionality is just lots of Clojure code and very little Emacs Lisp
code. I&rsquo;m reasonably sure I&rsquo;m one of the very few CIDER users who
knows more Emacs Lisp than Clojure, so I consider this a big win.</p></li>
<li><p>It&rsquo;s now easy to provide pretty similar level of support for both
Clojure and ClojureScript as we can reconcile the differences
between them in our middleware.</p></li>
<li><p>It&rsquo;s easier to keep the code backwards compatible (which is a
nightmare for inlined code).</p></li>
<li><p>There are no implicit dependencies in the system (unlike before).</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Consider auto-completion &ndash; this feature was implemented in terms of
evaluating some <code>clojure-complete</code> code with the assumption that
<code>clojure-complete</code> is available in the environment you were using as
CIDER assumed you had started the nREPL server using <code>lein repl</code>. This
would fire up a REPL-y REPL and <code>clojure-complete</code> is a REPL-y
dependency. Not everyone uses <code>lein repl</code>, though and REPL-y can always
switch to another completion library in the future.</p>

<p>If you connected CIDER to an embedded nREPL server,
you&rsquo;d be greeted by a missing class error, as most apps don&rsquo;t normally
depend on <code>clojure-complete</code>. You&rsquo;d be puzzled for a while, but eventually
you&rsquo;ll realize what the problem is.</p>

<p>Now we&rsquo;re free to explicitly specify our deps and pick the best
libraries for the job (as opposed to those that are available) &ndash;
you&rsquo;ll quickly notice how smarter auto-completion is now on Clojure,
because we&rsquo;re internally using the newer, faster and more feature-rich
<a href="https://github.com/alexander-yakushev/compliment">compliment</a> library
(note that we&rsquo;re using a different library for ClojureScript
completion).
* Other projects can leverage some of our middleware &ndash; somewhat
  amusingly for Emacs users, <code>vim-fireplace</code> is using <code>cider-nrepl</code>
  as well.</p>

<p>At this point we&rsquo;ve removed pretty much all inlined code (except some
pretty-printing code) and that has yielded much improved eldoc,
macroexpansion, documentation viewing (<code>cider-doc</code> will now display
Javadoc in Emacs!!!), source browsing, etc.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;ve also started bringing back some features we loved in SLIME, but
were missing so far &ndash; the inspector, apropos and tracing are back. We&rsquo;re now working on
bringing back function call cross-referencing and debugging as well.</p>

<p>Note that CIDER will still work if you connect to an nREPL server
that&rsquo;s not using CIDER&rsquo;s middleware. In this case you&rsquo;ll get a
warning and a pretty limited feature-set &ndash; source file loading, code
evaluation, pretty-printing and error highlighting.</p>

<h3>cider-test</h3>

<p><code>clojure-test-mode</code> (which was more or less abandoned in terms of
maintenance) finally has a successor in CIDER itself. <code>cider-test</code>
provides more or less the same functionality, but is implemented in
terms of nREPL middleware and is a more robust solution. As it&rsquo;s part
of CIDER it cannot ever be out-of-sync with CIDER as <code>clojure-test-mode</code> has
often been lately.</p>

<p><code>cider-test</code> is a little rough around the edges, but I&rsquo;m fairly sure it has bright future
ahead. Use it, love it, hate it and send us your feedback! We&rsquo;d love to hear it.</p>

<p><strong>P.S.</strong> We might extend this with support for other frameworks like
<code>midje</code> and <code>expectations</code>, although that&rsquo;s not high on our priority
list.</p>

<h3>Grimoire support</h3>

<p>In addition to built-in Clojure &amp; Javadoc you can now peruse the
extended documentation provided by
<a href="http://grimoire.arrdem.com/">Grimoire</a> from the comfort of your
beloved editor. No more browser interruptions just to get a few usage
examples of some function! <code>C-c C-d g</code> for the win!</p>

<p>Adding some extended Grimoire integration is definitely on the roadmap.</p>

<h3>Increased bus factor</h3>

<p>One of the biggest problems of the project so far was that fairly few people
were involved with it.  At one point it was mostly Tim, Hugo and
me. At another it was mostly me. The bus factor was dangerously close
to 1, which always worried me. Recently, however, a lot of people have
been helping quite actively, which makes me more optimistic about the
future. As much as I love CIDER I don&rsquo;t want it to depend on one
extremely busy and very clumsy person (each time I go hiking there&rsquo;s a
serious chance I&rsquo;ll fall of a cliff or something).</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d like to thank everyone for your wonderful contributions and single
out a bunch of people for some outstanding work done by them:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/gtrak">Gary Trakhman</a> is the one responsible for
the good ClojureScript support we now boast. Fantastic work, Gary! You have a big thanks from me!</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/jeffvalk">Jeff Valk</a> did some mighty fine work
on the var info retrieval, source navigation, documentation display
and single-handedly implemented <code>cider-test</code> and <code>cider-apropos</code>. We
all owe Jeff a huge thanks!</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/hugoduncan">Hugo Duncan</a> who constantly
  contributed patches, bug reports and ideas. His <code>nrepl-ritz</code>
  project provided a lot of inspiration for some of the existing
  middleware.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/eslick">Ian Eslick</a> contributed the new inspector.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/alexander-yakushev/compliment">Alexander Yakushev</a>
  made so many improvements to his awesome <code>compliment</code>
  library for the needs of CIDER. Did you notice that you now get
  completion suggestions for <strong>locals</strong>? How amazing is that!</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dgutov">Dmitry Gutov</a> implemented native support in CIDER for <code>company-mode</code>.</li>
</ul>


<h2>The Road Before Us</h2>

<p>Obviously our work is far from over &ndash; we&rsquo;re still lacking some crucial
features (most notably a debugger) and a lot of code needs
polish. This will obviously take some time and a lot of work to get right, but I&rsquo;m
confident we&rsquo;ll get there.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d also want us to work a bit in the area of documentation &ndash; a
manual, a cheatsheet, etc. Have a look at the
<a href="https://github.com/clojure-emacs/cider/issues">issue tracker</a> if
you&rsquo;d like to help out &ndash; we definitely need all the help we can get.</p>

<p>The 0.7 release required a massive amount of work and we spent more that 3 months to get it to
a shippable state. With the bulk of the work behind us I hope we&rsquo;ll be able to deliver new
releases more frequently &ndash; on a monthly (or bi-monthly) basis.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d love to be able to raise a lot of money via crowd-funding and work
on CIDER for an year or get hired by some company to work full-time on
it, but that&rsquo;s not going to happen. For one reason or another people
rarely get excited about dev tools, so all of us have to work together
to make CIDER the ultimate Clojure(Script) development environment.</p>

<p>If I knew how much work I&rsquo;d have to do when I assumed the maintenance
of CIDER exactly one year ago I might not have done it. Maintaining a
project that&rsquo;s pivotal to an entire community (I recall some article
mentioning about half the Clojure devs were using it) is both a lot of
work and a lot of stress and pressure. That said, it&rsquo;s probably my
favourite OSS project and I enjoy working on it immensely. If you
don&rsquo;t have the time to help out with code or docs you can still support my
work on CIDER (and all my other projects) via
<a href="https://www.gittip.com/bbatsov">gittip</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.gittip.com/bbatsov"><img src="https://rawgithub.com/twolfson/gittip-badge/0.2.0/dist/gittip.png" alt="Support via Gittip" /></a></p>

<p>For all the gory details regarding new features and changes in CIDER 0.7 &ndash; take a look at the
<a href="https://github.com/clojure-emacs/cider/blob/master/CHANGELOG.md">changelog</a>.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s all from me, folks! Use CIDER, drink cider and prosper!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
