<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Rant | (think)]]></title>
  <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/categories/rant/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://batsov.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-15T11:05:28+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://batsov.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bozhidar Batsov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Die EmacsWiki, Die!]]></title>
    <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/2012/03/20/die-emacswiki/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-20T14:49:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://batsov.com/articles/2012/03/20/die-emacswiki</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Prelude</h2>

<p>Emacs is slowly, but firmly moving in the right direction with
<a href="http://batsov.com/articles/2011/08/19/a-peek-at-emacs24/">Emacs 24</a>. A
lot of new important features are coming, the release date is nearing,
but there is something worrisome on the otherwise bright Emacs
horizon. It&rsquo;s a remnant from the <strong>Dark Emacs Days</strong> and it&rsquo;s called
<a href="http://emacswiki.org">EmacsWiki</a>.</p>

<p>Shortly put &ndash; <em>EmacsWiki is a blight</em>.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>A Little Bit of Background</h2>

<p>Here&rsquo;s the longer story. EmacsWiki was created by
<a href="http://www.emacswiki.org/alex/">Alex Schroeder</a> (aka <strong>kensanata</strong>)
way back (in 2001) with the goal to become the home of all the Emacs
information one would ever need (both about Emacs in general and its
extensions). I have to admit that this was a noble goal and I know that
Alex had all the right intentions, but unfortunately right intentions
rarely are enough for things to always move in the right
direction.</p>

<p>The software behind the wiki is called
<a href="http://www.oddmuse.org/cgi-bin/oddmuse">OddMuse</a> and it&rsquo;s authored by
Alex himself. It&rsquo;s pretty basic Perl script and doesn&rsquo;t feature db
support. Its motto is <em>No MySQL; no PostgreSQL; no worries.</em> &ndash; wish it
were true&hellip;</p>

<h2>The Problems</h2>

<p>The EmacsWiki has several epic problems. Here we go:</p>

<h3>Odd Choice for a Wiki</h3>

<p>Even if in the beginning OddMuse might have been a good choice (Alex
authored it and MediaWiki didn&rsquo;t exist back then), it hasn&rsquo;t been a
good choice for quite a while. There are much better solutions in
terms of markup support (Markdown anyone?), usability and
performance. Some of the features of the wiki are simply abhorring &ndash;
like the lack of user access control; anyone can enter any user name and
edit the wiki&hellip; Yep, this is not a joke&hellip;</p>

<h3>Moderators, Where Art Though?</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;ve never seen so much junk in a wiki in my entire life (and I&rsquo;ve
seen the wikis of 15-year enterprise systems). When I was
an Emacs beginner I often consulted the wiki for advice &ndash; even then I
noticed that there were some suspicious practices being suggested
there. Now I can say with certainly that much of the content there is
total bullshit &ndash; it&rsquo;s mostly written by people with very little
knowledge of Emacs (not to mention good Emacs practices). The articles
are littered with crappy advice confusing beginners, have little
structure and are filled with ridiculous questions (questions in an
wiki???). All of this would have been avoided had the EmacsWiki had a
team of moderators to keep shitty contributions at bay. Alas, such a
team does not exist (or does a very crappy job of it).</p>

<h3>Software Distribution Medium</h3>

<p>As crazy as it seems a lot of people are using the wiki as a software
distribution mechanism. Instead of hosting their projects in version
control (say <a href="http://github.com">GitHub</a>) they develop stuff locally,
upload them to the wiki and say that this is the canonical way to
obtain their software. Needless to say &ndash; this is a horrible, horrible
practice. I&rsquo;ve often encountered on the wiki source files authored by
someone, then edited by 10 different guys, that have a tendency to add
their names to the copyrights sections instead of thinking how their
poor users will understand what exactly was changed in these
files. Sometimes the authors themselves are to blame (for being
fucking lazy), but often someone just copies a snapshot of a project
from version control and uploads it to the wiki, creating problems of
epic proportions for the maintainers, who start receiving bugs about
stuff they never developed in the first place.</p>

<p>For the love of God &ndash; take your project(s) to GitHub and develop them
there with pleasure, under the scrutiny of an active and passionate
developer community. Wikis should be used for documentation only!</p>

<p>Tools like audo-install (an extension that supports installing
software from EmacsWiki) should never have existed. el-get should not
have added support for the installation of stuff from the wiki. As
long as such practices are tolerated they will not stop.</p>

<p>Need I remind you that we&rsquo;re now living in the era of
<a href="http://batsov.com/articles/2012/02/19/package-management-in-emacs-the-good-the-bad-and-the-ugly/">package.el</a>
and distributed version control (Git, Mercurial, Bazaar)? Act accordingly!</p>

<h3>Jack of All Trades</h3>

<p>Documenting each and every Emacs project is an impossible task. And it
should not be centralized. Each project should be responsible for
producing its own up-to-date easy-to-follow crystal-clear
documentation. By putting everything in one place you&rsquo;re just making
sure you&rsquo;ll end up with a pile of out-of-date confusing unstructured
ramblings (the EmacsWiki proves my point).</p>

<p>An EmacsWiki shouldn&rsquo;t list tips on the use of external projects &ndash;
such tips should be in the project&rsquo;s wiki. An EmacsWiki should
document the core Emacs experience and customizations only.</p>

<h2>The Solution</h2>

<p>Kill the EmacsWiki! (may it be reborn from its ashes)</p>

<h3>Action Plan for The Maintainers</h3>

<p>Drop the current format of the wiki &ndash; use something standard like
MediaWiki instead of OddMuse. Drop all the articles about Emacs
extensions. Drop all the extensions hosted there. Assemble
a team of moderators. Accept only articles about general Emacs usage
and Emacs Lisp programming.</p>

<h3>Action Plan for Emacs Extensions Authors</h3>

<p>If you&rsquo;ve got a normal project hosted on GitHub (or a similar service)
&ndash; delete everything about your project on the wiki and don&rsquo;t respond
to any bug requests regarding modified copies of your sources
distributed via EmacsWiki.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;ve got a project hosted on the EmacsWiki &ndash; there is still
a chance for you to redeem yourself. Migrate your project(s) to GitHub
(you&rsquo;ll thank me later for that). Use their version control, their
issue tracker, their wiki system. Start distributing your project via
Marmalade or MELPA (<code>package.el</code> repos). Your life will become much nicer and
the visibility of your project and the possibility to attract new
developers will be significantly boosted. GitHub is a project hosting
solution, the EmacsWiki is not.</p>

<h3>The Regular Users</h3>

<p>Boycott the wiki (unless the maintainers take actions)! Submit
documentation only to the official project pages. Ignore projects
hosted on the EmacsWiki. (or migrate them to GitHub if they seem
orphaned and try to rekindle them)</p>

<h2>Epilogue</h2>

<p>Do we need an EmacsWiki? Certainly we do! But we need a <strong>real</strong>
EmacsWiki and not this abomination that is currently a detriment to
new Emacs users, instead of help. The wiki needs restructuring, but
first it needs to die. I hope you&rsquo;ll see the truth in my words and
take action instead of commenting how outrageous my claims are. Do
something meaningful for a change &ndash; save a project from the EmacsWiki,
contribute documentation to an official project&rsquo;s wiki, package
something on Marmalade&hellip;</p>

<p>Die, Die EmacsWiki! I&rsquo;ll be seeing you in hell&hellip;</p>

<p><strong>Update</strong></p>

<p>This post stirred a huge discussion online and as a result there is
now another Emacs wiki out there. The new wiki is available at
<a href="http://wikemacs.org">http://wikemacs.org</a>. It&rsquo;s using MediaWiki (it
turned out it had several nice advantages over MoinMoin).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Linux desktop experience is killing Linux on the desktop, Part II]]></title>
    <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/2011/06/14/linux-desktop-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-14T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://batsov.com/articles/2011/06/14/linux-desktop-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Read this with an open mind.</em></p>

<h2>Prelude</h2>

<p>A few days back I wrote a somewhat controversial article called,
<a href="/Linux/Windows/Rant/2011/06/11/linux-desktop-experience-killing-linux-on-the-desktop.html">&ldquo;The Linux desktop experience is killing Linux on the desktop&rdquo;</a>. While
many readers seem to have grasped the true purpose of the article, a
lot of people claimed that it was nothing but FUD (a favorite term
of many people in the Linux community, who would rather ignore
existing problems than face/acknowledge them).</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;ve read my last post and generally agree with it &ndash; don&rsquo;t bother
reading this one. It&rsquo;s basically more of the same &ndash; in greater detail
and with less profanities.</p>

<p>In this article I&rsquo;ll have a look at the state of the Linux desktop,
it&rsquo;s usability, strengths and weaknesses.</p>

<h2>Let&rsquo;s get some facts straight</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m writing this post from my Emacs 23.2 client (in Markdown, to
publish it via git to my jekyll powered blog) connected to my Emacs
daemon, running on my Fedora 15 GNOME 3.0 desktop at home. This
machine has its every part carefully selected for maximum Linux
compatibility (the machine is a bit old, but that wasn&rsquo;t always the case) &ndash;
a GeForce 9600GT known to work &ldquo;great&rdquo; with the open-source nouveau
driver, an Asus Xonar DX sound card, supported by the great Oxygen HD
audio driver, etc. I do know how to buy hardware (contrary to popular
belief). Actually I&rsquo;ve been a hardware
enthusiast for most of my life and I know much more about the inner
workings of computer components than most people. That said &ndash; the hardware that
I bought for my home PC was not the hardware that I wanted to buy, but
the one I had to buy.</p>

<p>Even the ill-fated T520 Sandy Bridge laptop was supposed to work very
well with Linux &ndash; after all Intel and Nvidia video cards are the
safest bet in town.</p>

<p>One of the great things about using a free (as in speech) OS like
Linux is that you get to do things exactly the way you want to do
them. You&rsquo;re in control. Everything is transparent. Nothing magically
happens behind the scenes. It&rsquo;s sad that this
doesn&rsquo;t extend to the ability to pick any piece of fairly generic
hardware and properly enjoy it. Often you just have to hope
and pray &ndash; and sometimes you might get lucky.</p>

<p>A reader pointed me to
<a href="http://blog.eracc.com/2011/06/14/the-century-of-the-linux-desktop/">this piece</a>
&ndash; a rebuttal of my article. Here&rsquo;s an excerpt:</p>

<p><em>Here we go again. Some fellow has gotten all whiny about being such a
big Linux fan, &ldquo;… hardcore Linux user …&rdquo;, but he just had to go back
to Microsoft to get things done. Why? Because he is tired of having to
tinker with Fedora Linux to make things work, or fail to work, with
cutting edge hardware … and 64-bit Flash on 64-bit Linux is sucky …
and Skype on Linux is sucky … and … and … and. It was all just so
painful and time consuming he could not take it any longer and went
back to the safe arms of Microsoft to escape the horror that is
Linux. Good grief.
Okay, first and foremost, a true &ldquo;hardcore Linux user&rdquo;, in my mind a
fan of Linux, is unlikely to switch from Linux to anything else. Oh
yes, he or she will switch Linux distributions in a heartbeat, or
maybe three heartbeats, if a distribution fails to work as needed. But
switching to Microsoft and leaving the Linux desktop behind? Not
likely, my friends. I consider myself a true &ldquo;hardcore Linux user&rdquo; and
I see no voluntary switch from Linux in my future … ever.</em></p>

<p>This bit produced a sad smile on my face. Had to go back to Microsoft?
Absolutely not! Chose to use Windows 7 (for the time
being)&hellip; If I was to go back to something it should have been FreeBSD
since it was the OS I was using before Linux (and of course Windows
before that indeed). I actually switched quite reluctantly from
FreeBSD to Linux for a simple reason &ndash; Linux supported wider hardware
variety and there were more native apps for it.</p>

<p>All Unix-derived OSes are more or less the same from an user&rsquo;s
perspective &ndash; mostly the same environment, the same applications. The
only thing that really makes the difference is the hardware support
and Linux is clearly far ahead of its competition.</p>

<p>Hardcore user? You bet! But hardcore doesn&rsquo;t mean an &lsquo;unreasonable
idiot, blinded by zealously&rsquo;. It&rsquo;s not always that someone&rsquo;s favorite
technologies are the best solution to a problem. The section &ldquo;the shit
I&rsquo;ve endured&rdquo; had a dual purpose &ndash; list a &ldquo;few&rdquo; problems and show how
resilient I am.</p>

<p>Distro hopping is something that mostly newbies do, because they fail
to grasp a fundamental thing in the land of Linux &ndash; 95% of the stuff
that comprises a distribution is generic stuff found in most other
distros. You cannot seriously expect that the same drivers in a
different distro will yield wildly different results&hellip; Sure, bugs do
tend to occur, and sometimes they are truly distribution
specific. Sure, some distros happen to patch the stuff they ship
heavily, while others favor shipping vanilla versions of both software ant
the kernel.</p>

<h2>The process of driver development</h2>

<p>My former post placed a heavy emphasis on existing driver
issues. While I abhor some Linux drivers I&rsquo;ve never ever blamed the
authors of open source drivers. Here&rsquo;s why:</p>

<p>The year and a half I&rsquo;ve spent writing Linux drivers for a proprietary
Austrian company was some of the hardest time in my professional
career. Writing drivers is fairly hard task for two reasons &ndash; you have
to have very intimate knowledge of the hardware at hand and you have
to write very safe code (and carefully test it), because otherwise you might bring the whole
kernel down. I was basically reading tech specs (most boring read in
the world) most of the day and
writing very little code in end. Debugging drivers is not a pleasant
task either.</p>

<p>Linux certainly has some of the best developers in the world. I have
little doubt in that. The problem is that these same developers spent
their days working other jobs and you cannot seriously expect them to
have the time or the energy (not to mention the specs required) to
produce drivers that are on par with commercial counterparts developed
for OSX and Windows by big team with vast resources at their disposal.</p>

<p>This is the actual problem as I see it &ndash; we&rsquo;re expecting individuals
to create good drivers for us out the kindness of their hearts in
their little spare time with little or no hardware specs on which to
rely for absolutely no money.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve read the source code of many network layer drivers in the Linux
kernel and I&rsquo;ve noticed a common trend &ndash; a lot of the drivers were
actually written by hardware engineers (instead of software engineers)
&ndash; they are filled with copy/paste segments from other drivers, lots of
  useless/dubious/dangerous code. This doesn&rsquo;t surprise me &ndash; few
  software engineers have solid grasp of hardware and/or the will to
  take part in driver development. This is a big problem with no easy solution.</p>

<p>The hardware vendors are the only party that deserves blame for the
sorry state of many drivers. I cannot believe how hard it is for a
company with the size of AMD to deliver a decent Linux driver
for so many years. Their driver is a monument of everything that is
wrong with hardware vendors as far as Linux is concerned &ndash; no support
for latest kernels/X, no support for current state-of-the-art Linux
video technologies, notorious instability and performance. Nvidia fare
a lot better but still &ndash; their driver lacks the support basic stuff
such as KMS&hellip;</p>

<p>So what can we do? Obviously not everyone can start writing better
drivers, but still everyone could try to help&hellip;</p>

<p>For most desktop hardware vendors Linux is a non-existing OS. Linux
truly has a small market share, but that is not the actual
problem. The actual problem is that Linux desktop user would rather
wait for someone from the community to come up with a solution instead
of the pressure the vendors into action. Fill their mailboxes with angry
letters, write blog posts about their inadequacy to properly support
the third largest desktop OS in the world. Companies love to make
money and hate bad press&hellip;</p>

<h2>The desktop software stack</h2>

<p>The Linux desktop stack has some great qualities &ndash; for instance it
often comes with batteries included. You have most of your day to day
need covered as soon as you install your distro &ndash; a decent browser, a
good email client, an office suit, disk burning utility, torrent
downloader, IM client, text editors, photo organizers, image editors,
etc. When I installed Windows 7 I was a bit surprised how bare the
initial installation is and how many third party apps I needed to
install. And of course most of the Linux desktop apps coming from the
same environment (KDE, GNOME, XFCE, etc) have a very uniform look and
feel to them which I personally value a lot.</p>

<p>Unfortunately not everything is great&hellip;</p>

<p>The Linux desktop application stack suffers from a few serious
problems:</p>

<ul>
<li>a few individuals make crucial decisions without taking any input
from the user community</li>
<li>many projects have only one principle developer that happens to do
things his way without regard for anyone else</li>
<li>often highly unstable beta quality software is pushed as stable to
the end users</li>
<li>a lot of prominent apps that are multi-platform seem to undergo
sub-par testing/QA process under Linux and experience common problems
like crashes and memory leaks that don&rsquo;t manifest that often on
other platforms</li>
</ul>


<p>In more details&hellip;</p>

<p><strong>Is it really better for the users?</strong></p>

<p>Often a new feature arrives that is marketed as a huge improvement for
the end-users. Most of the time the end-users are never inquired about
their opinion of the feature. PulseAudio is a great example. I was
pretty happy using ALSA directly, but nobody asked me what I thought
about the change. Initially it was fairly easy to disable pulse audio,
but as it became more and more integrated into the desktops the
process became harder (luckily pulse audio improved in the
process). While I&rsquo;m perfectly aware of the technical reasoning that
lead to pulse audio&rsquo;s creation I do find it rather useless. With only
one major architecture left (almost no one uses OSS on Linux these
days) the introduction of intermediate sound layer of dubious quality
never made that much sense to me. Sure, ALSA needed a simpler API, but
we didn&rsquo;t deserve to be punished with pulse audio&hellip;</p>

<p><strong>It&rsquo;s my way or the highway</strong></p>

<p>Most of you probably remember that Pidgin (formerly Gaim) used to be
the default IM client in GNOME based distros. At some point this
quickly changed and Empathy became the default client. Part of the
reason for the switch was the unwillingness of the lead developer in the
Pidgin project to collaborate with the GNOME developers. I still
remember the controversial fix that made the input area non-resizable
with no option to go back to the previous setting. I guess GNOME&rsquo;s
devs were really pissed about something since they replaced the all around great
Pidgin with a vastly inferior and immensely buggy (at least for the
first year and a half) product.</p>

<p>Too much power of the hands of a single person with no overseer is
dangerous. In the open-source world one can easily fork a project, but
this is a dangerous path as well that is often likely to wreak havoc
into the development of the project.</p>

<p><strong>Are we your users or your beta testers?</strong></p>

<p>A few examples from recent years:</p>

<p>KDE 4.0</p>

<p>GNOME 3.0</p>

<p>Empathy</p>

<p>PulseAudio</p>

<p>NetworkManager</p>

<p>Beagle</p>

<p>The list could go on and on&hellip; Microsoft and Apple have certainly had
their fair share of mistakes (Win ME, Win Vista, OS X Leopard), but
nothing on a scale as epic as KDE 4.0 or GNOME 3.0&hellip;</p>

<p><strong>Some users are more important then others it seems&hellip;</strong></p>

<p>All those programs run on all major OS, but they perform worst on Linux:</p>

<p>Firefox</p>

<p>OpenOffice</p>

<p>Flash Player</p>

<p>Obviously writing great multi-platform apps is possible as illustrated
by software such as VLC and Google Chrome. But what about all the
rest. I feel that Firefox&rsquo;s days as the dominant browser on the Linux
desktop are numbered &ndash; most of my friends that use Linux have already
switched to Chrome (or the open source Chromium). Firefox on Linux is
like a bad joke &ndash; slow, memory hungry and unstable. I keep hearing
that it runs a lot better on OSX and Windows, probably because it got
a lot more testing on those platforms. I understand their reasoning &ndash;
most of their clients use those two OSes so it makes sense to make them
important in the dev/testing phases. But they should remember
something &ndash; Firefox is (for now) the default
browser only in most Linux distros and it&rsquo;s never going to be the
default in Windows or OSX&hellip;</p>

<p>Same goes for OpenOffice to the letter.</p>

<p>And flash is well &ndash;
flash. It&rsquo;s not the greatest piece of software on any platform, but
it&rsquo;s absolutely horrible in Linux. When I open a flash intensive web
site my CPU load generally spikes up to the sky (thank God for AdBlock
&amp; FlashBlock).</p>

<p>Skype was not even mentioned here (until now obviously) since the Linux version is so far behind
the one for OSX and Windows that I wouldn&rsquo;t even consider it a
port. It&rsquo;s just some pile of crap compiled to be able to list Linux as
a supported OS on their website&hellip; They promised improvements, they
promised an open-source Linux client &ndash; two years later we&rsquo;re still
using Skype 2.1 BETA. I wish more people had the sense to use a
service like Google Talk so I wouldn&rsquo;t have to put up with skype at all.</p>

<h2>The community (communist) model</h2>

<p>I live in a country from the former Soviet block (Bulgaria) and I&rsquo;ve seen first
hand what Communism leads to. I&rsquo;ve also seen first-hand why Communism
doesn&rsquo;t actually work &ndash; few people actually live and abide by it and
the rest of society simply practices the fine art of &ldquo;getting by&rdquo; and
lives on their shoulders. The Communism can only really work if
everyone is pulling their own weight in it (which sounds a bit absurd indeed).</p>

<p>Something similar is happening on the Linux desktop ship &ndash; everybody
says he&rsquo;s on board, but very few people are actually rowing and
bringing the Linux desktop to it&rsquo;s designated port.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve written only two desktop project for Linux from scratch (an
English-Bulgarian dictionary utility and a GUI front-end for pacman on
Arch Linux), but I&rsquo;ve contributed bug reports and patches to lots of
projects. No matter what your opinion about me is &ndash; I&rsquo;ve done
something for the Linux desktop and I&rsquo;m doing something for the desktop now
as well &ndash; writing this article&hellip;</p>

<p>What have you done? Sure, very few users are software engineers, but
that doesn&rsquo;t mean they can&rsquo;t help. Bug reports are just as important
as patches. Ideas and suggestions for improvements are highly valued
as well. Don&rsquo;t sit in the shadows doing nothing &ndash; step into the light
and do something to help your favorite project get a little bit
better.</p>

<p>Step by step. Fix by fix. Improvement by improvement. This is how good
software gets created.</p>

<p>The bottom line is &ndash; the more of us that pitch in the fight for a
proper Linux desktop experience, the bigger the chances of the dream
becoming reality become.</p>

<h2>Future</h2>

<p>Unless something radically changes in the near future I don&rsquo;t see how
Linux can rise up to be a mainstream desktop OS. With very few
companies having any stakes in the Linux desktop that isn&rsquo;t happening
any time soon. I find a somewhat troubling trend in recent years &ndash; a
lot of companies that worked for a better desktop experience are now
gone. Ximian (the company behind GNOME) was purchased by Novell and
later Novell crumbled, making the future of one of the most popular
desktop distributions OpenSUSE doubtful. Mandrake was once one of the
most powerful Linux companies and Mandrake Linux was widely
used. Currently Mandriva is constantly on the brink of
bankruptcy. There are many other examples &ndash; Xandros, VidaLinux,
etc&hellip; Even the &ldquo;mighty&rdquo; Canonical struggles to build a successful
business model around their widely successful Ubuntu OS.</p>

<p>Desktop Linux has to be made somehow profitable for companies to start
investing more heavily in it. This is the hard, but honest truth. As
long as the primarily development is carried out with little (or no
funding), mostly by volunteers the hour of the desktop Linux will
never come.</p>

<p>There is one more serious problem &ndash; diversity. There are two many
distributions bring too little value to the table. The time spent
repacking the same software for a hundred distros could be better
utilized developing new applications/drivers and improving existing
ones. We need to have at least a couple rock solid desktop
distros/environments, otherwise the whole diversity thing means
basically nothing.</p>

<p>Few good options are worth more than a million half-baked options!</p>

<h2>Epilogue</h2>

<p>This article (and the one before it) was never about jumping the
ship, claiming that Windows or OSX are better than Linux or spreading
&ldquo;FUD&rdquo; (if I totally hate a term this is the one). It was always about
raising the awareness of existing issues in the land of desktop
Linux. After all just a few days before <a href="/Linux/Fedora/2011/05/31/fedora-15-tips.html">I had written a post
installation guide for Fedora 15</a>.</p>

<p>While I was writing the last paragraph I got another GNOME 3 shell corruption (time
for killall gnome-shell to take the stage) on my totally supported
hardware&hellip; A skype sound notification interrupted the song I was
listening to (thanks a lot, PulseAudio)&hellip; And yet I&rsquo;m still here. I
did switch to Windows 7 on my laptop and I do intend to use Window 7
at least for a while there. It&rsquo;s not perfect either, trust me about
that. Poor terminal emulator (though great PowerShell), a few random
application crashes (but these happen in Linux as well in recent
years) just to name a few.</p>

<p>The Linux desktop is at the edge of a cliff now. It&rsquo;s up to us to
decide whether we would save it or push it over the edge.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Linux desktop experience is killing Linux on the desktop]]></title>
    <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/2011/06/11/linux-desktop-experience-killing-linux-on-the-desktop/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-11T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://batsov.com/articles/2011/06/11/linux-desktop-experience-killing-linux-on-the-desktop</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong></p>

<p><em>This post is a bona fide rant. It tells how a hardcore Linux user
(me) decided to abandon Linux as a desktop platform and the reasons
behind this decision. It might provoke some controversy, but
I frankly don&rsquo;t care.</em></p>

<h2>Prelude</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m generally known as one of the biggest supporters of GNU/Linux,
I&rsquo;ve taught courses on Linux administration, I&rsquo;ve spoken at Linux
conferences and I naturally use Linux as my primary desktop on all my
machines. Well, that last part is not so true anymore. Here the story
begins&hellip;</p>

<h2>The background</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been using GNU/Linux exclusively for 8 years now. I&rsquo;ve spent a
lot of time with Fedora, Gentoo and Arch Linux. I use it at home, I
use it at work and along the way I&rsquo;ve converted many Windows users to
Linux. I&rsquo;ve lived through a lot of driver and software problems
with Linux, hoping that the day would come when it will become a
first-class citizen of the desktop operating systems town. Alas, this
day never came and probably never will.</p>

<p>My patience ended this week and I&rsquo;ll be gradually moving all my
desktop machines back to Windows. What caused me to take such drastic
course of action? I&rsquo;ve bought myself a new ThinkPad T520 laptop,
powered by Nvidia&rsquo;s Optimus GPU switching technology &ndash; when the GPU
load is low it uses the built-in Sandy Bridge GPU, when it gets higher
&ndash; it switches to the discrete NVS 4200M GPU. Needless to say &ndash; this
  technology is not supported under Linux, but I was prepared to live
  without it. After all both Intel and Nvidia are known to have decent
  Linux drivers so I was about to try both GPU and select the one with
  the better performance. All I had to do was pick a shiny new
  distribution to power my mobile powerhouse&hellip;</p>

<h2>The Distribution</h2>

<p>I love Fedora &ndash; always have, always will. They constantly deliver to
the end users the cutting edge in Linux technologies (both desktop and
server), so it&rsquo;s naturally my distro of choice (I&rsquo;m quite fond of
cutting edge tech). I installed on the new
laptop the latest Fedora 15 with GNOME 3.0 and here the problems
started. GNOME 3 requires 3d acceleration to work properly &ndash; a
reasonable requirement these days, at least on an operating system with
normal video drivers.</p>

<p>The Intel driver sucked so bad that I got constant screen corruption
and hang-ups. Too bad, because I preferred to use the Intel GPU since
I mostly work on the laptop. The open source Nvidia driver nouveau
doesn&rsquo;t support the NVS 4200, so I was forced to install the
proprietary driver. It ran OK initially, but after some time my system
just started to freeze while waiting for Plymouth (probably after some
kernel update, which I didn&rsquo;t notice). I could have tried the usual
tricks and fixed the problem, but at this point I finally realized how
idiotic it was of me to keep using Linux for a desktop OS after all
the shit I&rsquo;ve endured and the time I&rsquo;ve wasted dealing with stuff that
should have been &ldquo;just working&rdquo;. I just want to get some work done, I
don&rsquo;t want to waste my time debugging all kind of crap.</p>

<h2>The Shit I endured</h2>

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong></p>

<p><em>I&rsquo;ve endured this Shit over the aforementioned period of 8
years. Some of the problems here have been alleviated (like
ethernet/wireless support) and some manifest mainly with newer
hardware (released in the past 6-12 months). Many of the problems,
unfortunately manifest on all kind of hardware no matter how old.</em></p>

<p><strong>Non-existing ethernet/wireless drivers</strong> &ndash; not so common today, but
  try remembering the time circa 2005</p>

<p><strong>Non-existing/crappy audio drivers</strong> &ndash; got an X-Fi 5 years ago, ALSA
  driver was released 3-4 years later and was total piece of garbage,
  OSS driver was barely usable. I don&rsquo;t even get me started on USB
  audio support &ndash; what a joke&hellip;</p>

<p><strong>Lamest video card drivers ever</strong> &ndash; most video card drivers for Linux
  are so bad I cannot even watch tear-free video. Nvidia have the only
  decent video driver, but it&rsquo;s far from perfect either &ndash; no KMS, poor
  2D acceleration. AMD&rsquo;s drivers are a punishment from the Lord and
  Intel&rsquo;s constantly &ldquo;evolving&rdquo; drivers are barely usable most of the
  time. The video card drivers made me buy and HD media player and an
  PS3 (for which I&rsquo;m thankful), but I have to ask myself &ndash; why suffer
  all this shit instead of getting a normal desktop OS like OS X or
  Windows? Did I love Linux that much? Did I believe that much it&rsquo;s
  desktop day would come? What an idiot I was.</p>

<p><strong>Lack of printer drivers</strong> &ndash; that&rsquo;s a funny one. Often printers
  listed as having Linux drivers are mostly unusable. The printer that
  own is listed as having a &ldquo;perfect&rdquo; Linux compatability in
  openprinting.org. If this is perfect I cannot begin to imagine what
  is &ldquo;poor&rdquo; compatibility.</p>

<p><strong>Crappiest suspend/resume support</strong> &ndash; laptop goes to sleep, but
  doesn&rsquo;t wake up. Wireless dies after wake up. Suspend/resume used to
  be something mythical to most Linux users. Recently the situation
  has improved a bit it&rsquo;s still light years away from what you get
  with Windows/OSX.</p>

<p><strong>Poor power management</strong> &ndash; my older laptop&rsquo;s battery lasted several
  weeks while sleeping when I was using Windows on it. When I replaced
  it with Linux the battery was being drained in 2 days while the
  laptop was sleeping (and I had to wait about half a year for a set
  of wireless and video drivers that actually made sleep a
  possibility)&hellip; I&rsquo;ve noticed that as far as dynamic power
  management is concerned Windows generally managed to squeeze more time
  out of the battery, while at the same time my rig generated less
  heat (dynamic fan control is another weakness of Linux).</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll stop writing about the driver problems now, because they affect
so many thing. Even my fairly advanced mouse is missing some functions
in Linux. I&rsquo;m not even mentioning the things like support for &ldquo;Turbo
Memory&rdquo;, Optimus, etc.</p>

<p><strong>Lack of decent office software</strong> &ndash; call it OpenOffice.org and don&rsquo;t
  insult it anymore&hellip;</p>

<p><strong>Problematic sound architecture</strong> &ndash; let me be completely blunt &ndash;
  everything sound related in Linux sucks &ndash; OSS, ALSA, PulseAudio (the
  sucker king). From a technical standpoint OSS never actually sucked,
  but since it wasn&rsquo;t picked up by the community the project fell
  into oblivion. How many of you have enjoy Dolby Digital or DTS sound
  from their Linux boxes?</p>

<p><strong>Poor flash support</strong> &ndash; should I explain? Have you tried it on a 64
  bit distro? Do I hate it? Sure. Do I hope HTML5 will kill it?
  Sure. Do I need it? Sure. You think your video drivers work OK under
  Linux? Have you tried playing a HD video clip in youtube with flash
  player at full-screen? Very few Linux video drivers handle this task properly&hellip;</p>

<p><strong>Poor skype support</strong> &ndash; Same story as with flash. I keep dreaming of
  a world with more intelligent users where GTalk has a conference
  mode and everybody&rsquo;s using it instead of skype.</p>

<p><strong>Poor quality of desktop apps</strong> &ndash; Known issues in core applications
  such as Nautilus don&rsquo;t get fixed for years. Such things naturally
  piss me off. Trying to contribute to the solution of a problem is
  often met with apathy by maintainers. Btw Linux users think that
  Mozilla Firefox is very slow and memory hungry &ndash; but it turns out
  that the Windows version is generally performing a lot better (not
  to mention &ndash; supporting hardware video acceleration).</p>

<p>I can keep listing things here forever. When I come to think about it
for the entire time I&rsquo;ve been using Linux only one major problem got
resolved &ndash; USB devices support. I still remember the days when I had
to write auto mounting policies myself or to use <em>mount</em> manually all
the time. I won&rsquo;t even mention the quality of most proprietary apps on
Linux, the huge amount of missing essential application and the
unavailability of mainstream video games.</p>

<p>So this is it! Hasta la vista, Linux! You still remain the best server
operating system, though. You&rsquo;ll always have a special place in my
heart and a VMWare instance on my Windows boxes.</p>

<h2>What I&rsquo;ll miss</h2>

<ul>
<li>shell</li>
<li>transparency, control</li>
<li>package management</li>
<li>lack of viruses, malware</li>
</ul>


<p>Although most common desktop users probably don&rsquo;t use the shell very
often, I practically live(d) in it. OS X has zsh and bash, so it&rsquo;s a
long term option for me, but due to the need for new hardware I&rsquo;ll be
using Windows 7 on the desktop front for now. Hopefully the rumors
that PowerShell is great will turned out to be true.</p>

<p>The ability to tweak every aspect of the configuration, to build
custom drivers and kernels will be missed as well, but I don&rsquo;t tend to
do this as often as I used to. And when something bad happens &ndash; most
of the time you could do something about it. As a friend of mine used
to say &ldquo;The single biggest difference between Windows and Linux is
that in Windows the restart will solve just about any problem, but in
Linux it&rsquo;s unlikely so solve any problem&rdquo; (this statement was much
more correct 8 years ago &ndash; modern Linux desktop distro have developed
some of Windows&rsquo;s old habits).</p>

<p>Probably the biggest loss for me would be the wonderful distro package
management systems like YUM and APT.</p>

<p>During the time I used Linux I totally forgot that things like viruses
and malware existed. Now, after I installed Win 7 I was immediately
encouraged to install an anti-virus program.</p>

<h2>Based on your feedback</h2>

<p>It seems a lot of people misunderstood the purpose of my rant so I&rsquo;d
like to clarify something for them:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>I <strong>fuckin'</strong> love Linux. Linux is brilliant. Linux is fun. Linux
rekindled my interest in computing at a time when I was about to
give up on computing.</p></li>
<li><p>I&rsquo;m not spreading FUD, I&rsquo;m telling you a real story, a story that I
know many have experienced and many will experience.</p></li>
<li><p>I&rsquo;m trying to raise the awareness of Linux desktop users. They&rsquo;ve
been told that they have to be thankful for any kind of hardware
support, no matter how basic, fucked up and all around shitty it
might be. They&rsquo;ve been told that they have to be grateful for every
crappy app in existence. The fact that something is free (as in
beer), doesn&rsquo;t make it wrong for people to criticize it and complain
about it. Ranting is what drives evolution. Same thing happens in
life every day &ndash; the media and the people around us proclaim
mediocrecy, they tell us that mediocrecy is OK, that we should be
satisfied by what we have and that aspiring for greatness is a
foolhardy mission. The Linux desktop community should put real
pressure on hardware and software vendors to be taken seriously,
instead of just waiting on their mercy. The Linux desktop community
deserves a great Linux desktop.</p></li>
<li><p>Fanatics are dangerous. They cannot see past their beliefs, they
cannot be reasoned with. The Linux community is full of them &ndash;
zealots that never see any problems with Linux and feel that the
entire world is on a quest to discredit their (mine) beloved
OS. They won&rsquo;t ever get this post, but hopefully YOU will.</p></li>
<li><p>Hardware support is a big part of the Linux desktop problem, but
it&rsquo;s not the only problem. Half-baked DE like KDE 4.0, Ubuntu&rsquo;s
Unity and GNOME 3.0 are just as dangerous.</p></li>
<li><p>Having some hardware support and having great hardware support are
two different things.</p></li>
<li><p>I do know how to research hardware compatibility ( :&ndash;) surprising,
eh?), but I do like
cutting edge technologies as well (problematic&hellip;). Does it seems
normal to you to avoid commodity hardware just on the ground that
it&rsquo;s &ldquo;too new&rdquo; to be properly employed by your OS of choice?</p></li>
<li><p>I&rsquo;m not claiming that Windows 7 is the greatest thing after hot
water, I don&rsquo;t even say that I like it. I do, however, say that it
offers superior desktop experience (when it works, that is).</p></li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;ll include here a great comment from Jan de Vos:</p>

<p>_While I&rsquo;m still using Linux (usually Ubuntu, sometimes Fedora)
everywhere (at work and at home), I do agree with a lot of points in
this article; there are a lot of things that could be improved, and
there are a lot of frustrations that Windows users don&rsquo;t have. Saying so
is not FUD, it is a simple truth. If someone who clearly likes a lot of
things in Linux decides to switch to something else, that really is a
bad thing, and an indication that there are real problems.</p>

<p>In my opinion, ignoring these problems, or even denying they exist, may
be a lot more harmful than talking about them._</p>

<p>I couldn&rsquo;t agree more!</p>

<h2>Epilogue</h2>

<p>I remember the first time I used Linux. A friend of mine installed
Fedora 2 on my personal computer and there was a glitch in GRUB that
prevented me from booting to Windows. My ethernet card wasn&rsquo;t
supported so I was left without Internet. I asked my friend can I at
least watch a few movies, while he brought me a patched version of the
buggy GRUB. He told me &ndash; you need to compile MPlayer from sources with
several optimization, you need windows video codecs, etc. At the time this
excited me a lot &ndash; adventure, excitement. I learned A LOT by using
Linux non-stop for so long time. But at some point you stop learning
exciting things and are just stuck with tedious things you have to
keep doing over and over again. And as I already mentioned &ndash; I don&rsquo;t
want my time wasted, I want to get the job done with minimum hassle.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been hearing each and every year that &ldquo;year 20xx&rdquo; will be the
year of the Linux desktop. It never came and it&rsquo;s my firm believe that
it never will (unless something radically changes in the mindset of
Linux desktop users). Constantly plagued by hardware and software woes Linux
is doomed to fail. Without major support from hardware and software
vendors every OS is ultimately doomed to fail.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s no secret that a lot of money are made by Linux server businesses
and this naturally drives a lot of the development in the area of
improving server performance. Nobody put it better than
<a href="http://apcmag.com/why_i_quit_kernel_developer_con_kolivas.htm">Con Colivas</a>
&ndash; &ldquo;<em>Linux is burdened with enterprise crap that makes it run poorly on
  desktop PCs.</em>&rdquo;. Linux will remain the king of the
  server world, but on the desktop front it will always be an OS for
  enthusiast and hackers only.</p>

<p>Goodbye, my dear old friend. You&rsquo;ll be missed&hellip; but not that much.</p>

<p>P.S. Btw I&rsquo;m as pro a Linux user as they get &ndash; a professional sys
admin, a former kernel developer so don&rsquo;t bother me with moronic
comments from the type &ldquo;you&rsquo;re not doing something right/you should
try another distro&rdquo;.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
