<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Fedora | (think)]]></title>
  <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/categories/fedora/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://batsov.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-29T10:29:21+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://batsov.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bozhidar Batsov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Running Xerox Phaser 3117 under Fedora 15]]></title>
    <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/2011/06/04/phaser-3117-fedora-15/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-04T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://batsov.com/articles/2011/06/04/phaser-3117-fedora-15</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been a GNU/Linux user for quite some time now and a Fedora user
for just as long. The first distribution that I ever used was Fedora 2
and even though I&rsquo;ve used extensively other distros I&rsquo;ve always come
back to Fedora. Recently Fedora 15 was released and I was
(naturally) one of the first people to install it.</p>

<p>Everything is great in the new release (as ever), but my Xerox Phaser
3117 printer is unsupported (also as ever) out of the box, so it&rsquo;s
time for one of those quick articles on how to get it up and running this
time. First run the following command as root (or with sudo):</p>

<p>``` bash</p>

<h1>yum install gutenprint-foomatic</h1>

<p>```</p>

<p>Now you can run the &ldquo;Printing&rdquo; application. It will autodetect your
printer and suggest you to use the driver for Xerox Phaser 3110. Just
accept this suggestion and you should be good to go. Happy printing!</p>

<p>P.S. You might also want to check out my article on
<a href="/Linux/Fedora/2011/05/31/fedora-15-tips.html">Fedora 15 post installation setup</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fedora 15 post installation setup & tips]]></title>
    <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/2011/05/31/fedora-15-tips/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-31T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://batsov.com/articles/2011/05/31/fedora-15-tips</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Prelude</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve recently upgraded all my systems to Fedora 15. The default
installation is not very usable for some tasks for several reasons &ndash;
like CD size limitations and software patents for instance. I also
happen to disagree with some defaults in Fedora like the fact that
sudo is not enabled by default (like in Ubuntu) and the use of the
bash shell. In this article I&rsquo;ll share some of the things I do after a
fresh Fedora 15 installation to enhance it (at least by my standards).</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Tweak defaults</h2>

<h4>Configure sudo</h4>

<p><code>sudo</code> gives you a way to execute single commands as the superuser. You
can also do this with <code>su -c</code>, but you have to quote the commands there,
which I don&rsquo;t like very much. To enable sudo for some account first
run the command:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ su -c "visudo"
</code></p>

<p>The file <code>/etc/sudoers</code> will open up in a customized vi editor. Append
somewhere to the end of the file the following line:</p>

<p><code>username ALL=(ALL) ALL</code></p>

<p>You should replace <em>username</em> with your username.</p>

<h4>Configure yum</h4>

<p>yum has a lot of plugins, but one of them is particularly useful &ndash; the
fastest mirror plug-in. You can install it like this:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo yum install yum-plugin-fastestmirror
</code></p>

<h4>Disable SELinux</h4>

<p>If you&rsquo;re a desktop Linux user you want to disable SELinux &ndash; trust
me. Open the file /etc/selinux/config and change this line:</p>

<p><code>SELINUX=enforcing</code></p>

<p>to</p>

<p><code>SELINUX=disabled</code></p>

<p>Restart afterwards.</p>

<h2>Install additional software</h2>

<p>Fedora&rsquo;s default installation medium is a 700MB CD. It&rsquo;s
understandable that not everything can be fitted in there. Luckily
adding new software from the vast Fedora on-line repos is child&rsquo;s play.</p>

<h4>Install REAL text editors</h4>

<p>gedit is ok for causal text editing, but professionals like software
engineers and system administrators will definitely need something more:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo yum install emacs vim
</code></p>

<p>Personally I use Emacs most of the time and use vim only to edit
config files that require root access.</p>

<h4>Install Z Shell</h4>

<p>It&rsquo;s no secret that I love the Z Shell &ndash; after all I <a href="/articles/2011/04/29/one-shell-to-rule-them-all/">rave about it</a>
quite often. It should come as no surprise that I happen to use it
and probably you should start using it as well:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo yum install zsh
$ sudo vim /etc/passwd
</code></p>

<p>Find the line about your account and change there /bin/bash to
/bin/zsh. Afterwards start a new login shell and a simple wizard will
fire up asking you some questions to create a default .zshrc file for you.</p>

<h4>Install LibreOffice</h4>

<p>LibreOffice is currently the best Linux option for word processing,
spreadsheet handling and presentation creation. You can install the
most common components with the following command:</p>

<p><code>bash
sudo yum install libreoffice-calc libreoffice-impress libreoffice-draw libreoffice-writer
</code></p>

<p>LibreOffice uses hunspell to do spellchecking. An English dictionary
will be installed by default, but you&rsquo;ll need to install additional
dictionaries manually:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo yum install hunspell-bg
</code></p>

<p>This command will install the Bulgarian hunspell dictionary. You
likely don&rsquo;t need it so install some more helpful dictionary instead. :&ndash;)</p>

<h4>Install OpenJDK</h4>

<p>If you need to run Java programs/applets:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo yum install java-1.6.0-openjdk java-1.6.0-openjdk-plugin
</code></p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re planning to do some Java development:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo yum install java-1.6.0-openjdk-devel java-1.6.0-openjdk-javadoc java-1.6.0-openjdk-src
</code></p>

<h4>Install Deluge torrent client</h4>

<p>The default Transmission torrent client is pretty basic. I recommend
you to replace it with the much more feature-rich deluge:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo yum install deluge
</code></p>

<h4>Install Inconsolata font</h4>

<p>I&rsquo;m a software engineer and I obviously spend a lot of time reading
and writing source code. I&rsquo;m very picking about the monospace font
that I use and currently Inconsolata happens to be my favorite:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo yum install levien-inconsolata-fonts
$ gsettings set org.gnome.desktop.interface monospace-font-name "Inconsolata 12"
</code></p>

<p>These two commands will install the font and make it the default
monospaced font on your Fedora system.</p>

<h4>Install GIMP</h4>

<p>Fedora does not ship with an image editor. GIMP is generally
considered the best option so you might want to install it:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo yum install gimp
</code></p>

<h4>Install gnome-tweak-tool to customize fonts, themes, etc in GNOME 3.0</h4>

<p>GNOME 3.0 has stripped many configuration options, but luckily most of
them are available by installing gnome-tweak-tool:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo yum install gnome-tweak-tool
</code></p>

<p>Run it (by pressing Alt+F2 and typing gnome-tweak-tool) and change the
settings. It does not have OK or Apply buttons, but simply selecting the
options performs the changes. Some changes may require logging out and
logging back in.</p>

<h2>Install additional patent encumbered/proprietary software</h2>

<h4>Enable RPMFusion</h4>

<p>RPMFusion is the most popular third party repository for Fedora. It&rsquo;s
full of goodness like audio/video codecs, proprietary drivers, etc. To
enable it just run the following command:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo yum localinstall --nogpgcheck \
http://download1.rpmfusion.org/free/fedora/rpmfusion-free-release-stable.noarch.rpm \
http://download1.rpmfusion.org/nonfree/fedora/rpmfusion-nonfree-release-stable.noarch.rpm
</code></p>

<h4>Install proprietary codecs</h4>

<p>No MP3 support in Fedora by default? And almost no video codecs?
RPMFusion to the rescue! Type this:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo yum install gstreamer-plugins-ugly gstreamer-plugins-bad gstreamer-ffmpeg
</code></p>

<h4>Install VLC</h4>

<p>With MPlayer&rsquo;s development in stagnation VLC has established itself as
the best video player for Linux recently. It&rsquo;s in RPMFusion, so if you
enabled it installing it is as easy as typing the following command:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo yum install vlc
</code></p>

<h4>Install Adobe Flash Player</h4>

<p>Love it or hate it &ndash; you probably need it.</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo rpm -Uvh http://linuxdownload.adobe.com/adobe-release/adobe-release-i386-1.0-1.noarch.rpm
$ sudo yum install flash-plug-in
</code></p>

<p>You can omit this if you&rsquo;re planning to use Google Chrome, since it
comes with Flash Player built-in.</p>

<h4>Install Skype</h4>

<p>Download Skype from the
<a href="http://www.skype.com/intl/en/get-skype/on-your-computer/linux/downloading.fedora">official site</a>. Assuming
you&rsquo;ve downloaded it to ~/Downloads, you can install it like this:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo yum localinstall Downloads/skype-2.2.0.25-fedora.i586.rpm
</code></p>

<p>Yum will automatically installed any dependencies required by skype.</p>

<h4>Install Oracle JDK</h4>

<p>OpenJDK is great, but due to licensing problems it&rsquo;s not quite the
same as the Oracle JDK. If you start experiencing strange problems
(mostly in Swing programs) you&rsquo;d probably do well to try the Oracle
JDK instead. Download Oracle&rsquo;s JDK from the
<a href="http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/javase/downloads/index.html">official site</a>. Select
&ldquo;Linux x86 &ndash; RPM Installer&rdquo; or &ldquo;Linux x64 &ndash; RPM Installer&rdquo; depending
on your distribution and install the JDK like this:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo sh jre-6u25-linux-i586-rpm.bin
</code></p>

<p>Fedora uses OpenJDK by default, so you&rsquo;ll have to do some more work to
tell it to start using Oracle JDK. The <strong>alternatives</strong> program allows
you to select between multiple installed versions of a program:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo alternatives --install /usr/bin/java java /usr/java/default/bin/java 1000
$ sudo alternatives --install /usr/bin/javac javac /usr/java/default/bin/javac 1000
$ sudo alternatives --install /usr/bin/javaws javaws /usr/java/default/bin/javaws 1000
</code></p>

<p>These commands will make alternative aware of the java binaries and
set high priorities to them which will make them the default Java
binaries. You can use &ldquo;alternatives &mdash;config binaryname&rdquo; to select
active binaries manually.</p>

<h4>Install Google Chrome</h4>

<p>Firefox is dying, Google Chrome is the new king of the
browsers. Download it from the <a href="http://www.google.com/chrome">official site</a> and install it:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo yum localinstall ~/Downloads/google-chrome-stable_current_i386.rpm
</code></p>

<p>Google Chrome will install a yum repository as well, so you&rsquo;ll receive
updates as soon as they arrive.</p>

<h4>Install DropBox</h4>

<p><a href="http://www.dropbox.com">DropBox</a> is a great file sharing service
which allows you to sync files between all of your computers and
mobile devices(Android, iPhone, iPad, etc). It has a great Linux
client which I use all the time. Download it from
<a href="http://www.dropbox.com/downloading?os=lnx">here</a> and install it like
this:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo yum localinstall --nogpgcheck nautilus-dropbox-0.6.7-1.fedora.i386.rpm
</code></p>

<h2>Epilogue</h2>

<p>Hopefully some of my setup has made your setup more enjoyable and more
productive. I&rsquo;ll update this article along the way if I stumble upon
other things that I consider to be generally helpful.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Enabling 3D support for Nouveau in Fedora 13]]></title>
    <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/2010/05/26/3d-support-nouveau-fedora-13/"/>
    <updated>2010-05-26T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://batsov.com/articles/2010/05/26/3d-support-nouveau-fedora-13</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Most of you probably have heard that Fedora 13 will feature
experimental 3D support for the Nouveau open source driver for Nvidia
cards. This support, however, is not enabled by default. To enable it
you need to install the mesa-dri-drivers-experimental package. I,
personally, do it like this(if you haven’t configured sudo, you’ll
have to perform this as root):</p>

<p><code>bash
sudo yum install mesa-dri-drivers-experimental
</code></p>

<p>Afterwards you can enable Compuz, play chromium-bsu or whatever your heart desires.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using Xerox Phaser 3117 on Fedora]]></title>
    <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/2009/09/25/xerox-phaser-3117-fedora/"/>
    <updated>2009-09-25T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://batsov.com/articles/2009/09/25/xerox-phaser-3117-fedora</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The driver selected by default by Fedora 11 is not appropriate for
Xerox Phaser 3117 &ndash; it will not print with it. However there is a very
easy solution to the problem.</p>

<p>Go to <strong>System &ndash;> Administration &ndash;> Printing</strong> (In GNOME at least, in KDE
it’s probably something similar). Right click the Xerox Phaser 3117
printer icon there and select &ldquo;Properties&rdquo; from the menu. Then in the
&ldquo;Make and model&rdquo; section choose change and then select Samsung
ML-1710.</p>

<p>After you apply the change you&rsquo;ve just made, you can start printing
with your Phaser.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Find out quickly which package provides a certain library with YUM]]></title>
    <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/2009/07/14/yum-provides/"/>
    <updated>2009-07-14T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://batsov.com/articles/2009/07/14/yum-provides</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the most dreaded things that you can see while trying to run
some application or trying to install an rpm package is a message
saying that some required library is missing.</p>

<p>Generally this is not a big problem, because most often the library
that you miss is packaged in a package named similarly to the
library. Sometime however this is not the case&hellip; Suppose for example
that you&rsquo;re trying to install IBM JDK 5.0 on a Fedora 11 box. You&rsquo;ll
most likely get the following error message:</p>

<p><code>bash
error: Failed dependencies:
libstdc++.so.5 is needed by ibm-java2-i386-sdk-5.0-9.0.i386
</code></p>

<p>and there is no package named libstdc++ that you can install, so how
can you find out which package do you need?</p>

<p>The answer is simple:</p>

<p>``` bash
$ yum provides libstdc++.so.5</p>

<p>Loaded plugins: fastestmirror, presto, refresh-packagekit
compat-libstdc++-33-3.2.3-66.i586 : Compatibility standard C++ libraries
Repo        : fedora
Matched from:
Other       : libstdc++.so.5
```</p>

<p>Pretty neat, eh?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
