<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Jekyll | (think)]]></title>
  <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/categories/jekyll/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://batsov.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-15T11:05:28+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://batsov.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bozhidar Batsov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blogging Like a Hacker: Evolution]]></title>
    <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/2011/11/11/blogging-like-a-hacker-evolution/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-11T08:52:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://batsov.com/articles/2011/11/11/blogging-like-a-hacker-evolution</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Prelude</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve started my personal blog some three years ago. Back then in was
hosted on <a href="http://wordpress.com">wordpress.com</a> and was called
devcraft.wordpress.com. I had a lot of interesting (at least to me)
topics to write about on my mind, but I was immediately faced with a
serious problem &ndash; I felt very uncomfortable writing posts in a small
text area, using the primitive editing capabilities of a web
browser. Ordinary decent hackers love and value two tools above all
else &ndash; their text editor and their shell. And we love solving problems
automatically with clever programs and scripts, instead of manually.</p>

<p>I knew the only way to ever start writing, like I intended, to was to
actively involve them in the process. So here my story begins&hellip;</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>In Emacs We Trust</h2>

<p>My editor happens to be Emacs and I&rsquo;ve started to look for ways to
blog without leaving its beloved frame. They were several options:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Use some browser extension that fires up Emacs when editing text
areas. For instance in Google Chrome there is the extension
<a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/ljobjlafonikaiipfkggjbhkghgicgoh">Edit with Emacs</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>Use <a href="http://orgmode.org/worg/org-blog-wiki.html">org-mode</a> to write my posts.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://mwolson.org/projects/EmacsMuse.html">Emacs Muse</a> was another
option. Emacs Muse is an authoring and publishing environment for
Emacs. It simplifies the process of writings documents and
publishing them to various output formats. Muse uses a very simple
Wiki-like format as input. Muse consists of two main parts: an
enhanced text-mode for authoring documents and navigating within
Muse projects, and a set of publishing styles for generating
different kinds of output.</p></li>
<li><p>Use some Emacs mode, like
<a href="http://www.emacswiki.org/emacs/WebloggerMode">weblogger-mode</a>, that
allows to write and publish WordPress (amongst others) entries directly from Emacs.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>All these options had their merits, but they also had their
shortcomings. For one &ndash; there is only one writer&rsquo;s markup that I
really enjoy and this is <a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/">Markdown</a>. This probably has something to do
with the fact that I&rsquo;ve written quite a lot of stuff in GitHub and
Assembla using it. I also wanted the ability to easily include syntax
highlighted code snippets (since I generally write about programming)
and handy way to manage blog updates &ndash; preferably via git. I push
something to my repo and voila.</p>

<p>At the time I couldn&rsquo;t make up my mind and my blog was left with a few
quite short posts, due to my inability to withstand being in wordpress
for any prolonged period of time.</p>

<p>Then something extraordinary happened in the beginning of this
year. I&rsquo;ve stumbled upon the post
<a href="http://tom.preston-werner.com/2008/11/17/blogging-like-a-hacker.html">&ldquo;Blogging Like a Hacker&rdquo;</a>
by GitHub&rsquo;s co-founder Tom Preston-Werner (aka mojombo). It seemed
that other people had exactly the same problem as me. It also seemed
they were more determined to do something about it.</p>

<h2>Along Comes Jekyll</h2>

<p>Long story short, Tom had written a blog aware static site generator,
called <a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</a> in Ruby. Jekyll
posts are simply Markdown or Textile files and the
<a href="http://liquidmarkup.org/">Liquid templating language</a> is used to
enhance the posts in their post-processing phase. Code highlighting?
Jekyll (and pygments) has got your back. Nice, ah? There is
support for various layouts and here&rsquo;s be best part &ndash; you could put
your blog in a GitHub repo and deploy automatically to GitHub Pages.</p>

<p>I instantly fell in love with Jekyll and as you can see from my
archive I&rsquo;ve finally wrote some nice (arguably) &amp; long articles &ndash; like I&rsquo;ve
originally intended.</p>

<p>While I was mostly happy with Jekyll there were a few things that
bothered me with it:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>You have to design your layouts yourself. While this is generally
fine if you have a sense for design, when you&rsquo;re someone like me
that could yield some pretty ugly designs. I was so out of ideas
that I designed my Jekyll layout to look like my Emacs (down to the
Zenburn color theme) for which I got a lot of flak.</p></li>
<li><p>Maruku is a really crappy Markdown processor. I wished something
like RedCarpet was the default and that fenced code blocks (ala
GitHub) were the default option for code highlighting. Not that you
can&rsquo;t replace Maruku with Kramdown or RedCarpet, but still. You&rsquo;d
also have to patch Jekyll to run albino on the markdown files to get
the highlighting to work with the fenced blocks.</p></li>
<li><p>You have to do some really boring stuff like Disqus integration,
twitter integration, etc manually (or at least you have to manually
install some plugins).</p></li>
<li><p>You have to unroll your own deployment scripts, since Jekyll doesn&rsquo;t
bundle any. Trivial task, but annoying non-the-less.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>So there you have it &ndash; Jekyll is very nice, but it&rsquo;s also very
barebone. My single biggest gripe with Jekyll, however, is that being
engineered by a GitHub guy it doesn&rsquo;t support out of the box the
GitHub flavored Markdown. At some point as I was seriously
contemplating starting a new static site generator, similar to Jekyll,
that supported only RedCarpet as the Markdown processor and by
extension &ndash; the GitHub flavoured Markdown. It would have some nice
default theme and very reasonable default settings for use in a
blog. Google Analytics, Twitter, Disqus would be supported out of the
box. But I never got to writing it since just before I started I was
introduced to Octopress&hellip;</p>

<h2>Octopress is Jekyll with Batteries Included</h2>

<p>Emacs users are typically portrayed like this:</p>

<p><img src="/images/articles/emacs_user.jpg"></p>

<p>I was naturally amused by the Octopress name.</p>

<p>First and foremost Octopress is Jekyll with batteries included. Some
of the nicer things include:</p>

<ul>
<li>A semantic HTML5 template</li>
<li>A Mobile friendly responsive (320 and up) layout (rotate, or resize your browser and see)</li>
<li>Built in 3rd party support for Twitter, Google Plus One, Disqus Comments, Pinboard, Delicious, and Google Analytics</li>
<li>An easy deployment strategy using Github pages or Rsync</li>
<li>Built in support for POW and Rack servers</li>
<li>Easy theming with Compass and Sass</li>
<li>A Beautiful Solarized syntax highlighting (though not as beautiful
as the Zenburn-one I&rsquo;m about to release soon)</li>
</ul>


<p>And did I mention that there are a lot of nice plugins included?</p>

<p>The default theme is quite nice, but you&rsquo;d probably want to tweak it a
bit (I still haven&rsquo;t &ndash; but my sense of design is nonexistent). It&rsquo;s
very easy to modify the theme.</p>

<p>I could go on and write a lot about Octopress, but there is no need to
do so. Go visit the official <a href="http://octopress.org">web site</a> &ndash; it has fantastic
documentation.</p>

<h2>Moving from Jekyll to Octopress</h2>

<p>Mostly trivial. I&rsquo;ve just copied my old Markdown posts, adjusted the
headings and the code blocks. And in the end all I had to do was:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ rake generate
$ rake deploy
</code></p>

<h2>Epilogue</h2>

<p>I love Octopress! I used to be a sad blogger and now I&rsquo;m a happy
blogger. If you&rsquo;re feeling like I felt &ndash; you should definitely give it
a shot. I&rsquo;ll probably do a few follow up articles with some tips &amp;
tricks I&rsquo;ve picked along the way with Octopress.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Add Atom feed to Jekyll powered blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/2011/04/24/add-atom-feed-to-jekyll/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-24T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://batsov.com/articles/2011/04/24/add-atom-feed-to-jekyll</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As you know I&rsquo;ve recently migrated my blog from WordPress to
Jekyll. One of the things I had to do was add an Atom feed(RSS
sucks). It was quite the easy task. I just had to create an
<a href="https://github.com/bbatsov/blog/blob/master/atom.xml">atom.xml</a> file
and place in the root of my blog.</p>

<p>Afterwards I only had to link my default layout to the atom feed:</p>

<p><code>xml
&lt;link rel="alternate" type="application/atom+xml" href="atom.xml" title="Atom feed"&gt;
</code></p>

<p>At this point I was able to subscribe to my new atom feed(and
hopefully my followers(which I may or may not have) were able to do
the same).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moving from WordPress to Jekyll]]></title>
    <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/2011/04/23/moving-to-jekyll/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-23T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://batsov.com/articles/2011/04/23/moving-to-jekyll</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is my first post after a very long hiatus partially induced by a
migration of my blog from WordPress to
<a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</a>, which I started half an
year ago and never quite finished(until today, that is).</p>

<p>I wasn&rsquo;t particularly unhappy with WordPress, but some things there
irritated me &ndash; for instance it was hard to edit my posts within my
beloved Emacs(and yes &ndash; I know all the options and I hate them
all). Accidentally I&rsquo;ve stumbled upon the post
<a href="http://tom.preston-werner.com/2008/11/17/blogging-like-a-hacker.html">&ldquo;Bloggin like a hacker&rdquo;</a>
and I instantly knew Jekyll was what I needed. It allows me to create
my posts as simple markdown templates, allows me to embed logic
written in Ruby in them and it has built-in support for code
highlighting(using the excellent Python library <em>pygments</em>). It also
allows me to store my blog under version control in github which is
really nice.</p>

<p>Jekyll is not particularly well documented and I had a few problems
with it at first, but I managed to overcome them all. One thing that
will be problematic for some users is the need to add things like rss,
commenting and analytics manually(they are bundled in a solution like
WordPress). On the other hand &ndash; you&rsquo;re not tied to anything in
particular and may choose the service you like the most. I chose
<a href="http://disqus.com">Disqus</a> for the comments and Google Analytics for the site
analytics(what a surprise).</p>

<p>By the way &ndash; my old blog Devcraft is no more. My new blog has a new
domain and a new theme(based on my favourite coding theme
<a href="https://github.com/bbatsov/zenburn-emacs">Zenburn</a>).  I know that the
blog is currently pig ugly and the content is not particularly great
either, but I&rsquo;ll try to improve this along the way and add a lot of
interesting and hopefully useful information.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
