<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Python | (think)]]></title>
  <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/categories/python/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://batsov.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-06-17T12:45:14+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://batsov.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bozhidar Batsov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Django 1.3 vs Rails 3: A not so final showdown]]></title>
    <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/2011/06/19/django-vs-rails/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-19T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://batsov.com/articles/2011/06/19/django-vs-rails</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Prelude</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve recently started a new job at an American start-up company. My
position in the company is the one of Technical Lead &ndash; the person responsible for
the selection of technologies around which the projects are being
built. Since we&rsquo;ll be doing mostly web development we&rsquo;ve had a long
kick-off discussion with the company&rsquo;s CTO about the direction which we should
initially take. He had PHP in mind, but I convinced him that Ruby or
Python would make much better platforms for our futures apps. So he
tasked me to research the two leading frameworks in the Ruby and
Python land &ndash; namely Ruby on Rails 3 and Django 1.3. I had a week to
prepare some prototypes with both and create on overview for my
boss. I had some experience with Rails 2 a few years back and I have
fairly decent knowledge of Ruby. My Python is not as fluent
(admittedly), but still &ndash; I&rsquo;ve played a lot with Python
recently. Django, however, was completely new to me. In this article
I&rsquo;ll try to compare the frameworks in a totally friendly way; if
you&rsquo;ve expected an epic flame war post you may very well stop reading
here. I&rsquo;m obviously no Rails/Django guru, so if I&rsquo;ve
written something that is wrong &ndash; please feel free to correct me.</p>

<p>Please, keep in mind that a short comparison article cannot even begin
to scratch the immense power and complexity of such frameworks. The overview,
that you&rsquo;ll find here is a bit on the superficial side, but it should
give you enough pointers to get you started.</p>

<p>Hopefully this article will be useful to people that are in the same
boat as was &ndash; picking between Rails and Django.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Setup &amp; Getting started</h2>

<h3>Rails</h3>

<h4>Linux &amp; OSX</h4>

<p>The recommended (by me) way to install Ruby and Ruby on Rails 3.x is via
<a href="https://rvm.beginrescueend.com/">RVM</a>. RVM allows you to have several
version of Ruby installed at the same time and to easily switch
between them. It also allows you to create gem sets, which are quite
handy in testing. After you&rsquo;ve installed RVM it&rsquo;s easy to install any
Ruby interpreter and Rails. This example shows how to get RVM, MRI 1.9.2
and Rails current (3.0.9):</p>

<p><code>bash
$ bash &lt; &lt;(curl -s https://rvm.beginrescueend.com/install/rvm)
$ echo '[[ -s "$HOME/.rvm/scripts/rvm" ]] &amp;&amp; . "$HOME/.rvm/scripts/rvm" # Load RVM function' &gt;&gt; ~/.bash_profile
$ source ~/.bash_profile
$ rvm install 1.9.2
$ rvm use 1.9.2 --default
$ which ruby
~/.rvm/rubies/ruby-1.9.2-p180/bin/ruby
$ ruby -v
ruby 1.9.2p180 (2011-02-18 revision 30909) [i686-linux]
$ gem install rails
$ rails -v
Rails 3.0.9
</code></p>

<p>Since RVM builds Ruby environments from source you might need to
install a few dependencies first. After you&rsquo;ve install RVM it will
output those packages as instructions.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re using Z Shell (like me) you should replace .bash_profile
with .zshenv or .zshrc.</p>

<h4>Windows</h4>

<p>While there are many ways to get Ruby on Rails installed on a Windows
host, the simplest is certainly to use the <a href="http://railsinstaller.org/">RailsInstaller</a>. It has only one
little drawback &ndash; currently it comes with Ruby 1.8.7 bundled, but the
recent beta already features Ruby 1.9.2.</p>

<h4>Your first Rails app</h4>

<p>``` bash
$ rails new railsdemo</p>

<pre><code>  create
  create  README
  create  Rakefile
  create  config.ru
  create  .gitignore
  create  Gemfile
  create  app
  create  app/controllers/application_controller.rb
  create  app/helpers/application_helper.rb
  create  app/mailers
  create  app/models
  create  app/views/layouts/application.html.erb
  create  config
  create  config/routes.rb
  create  config/application.rb
  create  config/environment.rb
  create  config/environments
  create  config/environments/development.rb
  create  config/environments/production.rb
  create  config/environments/test.rb
  create  config/initializers
  create  config/initializers/backtrace_silencers.rb
  create  config/initializers/inflections.rb
  create  config/initializers/mime_types.rb
  create  config/initializers/secret_token.rb
  create  config/initializers/session_store.rb
  create  config/locales
  create  config/locales/en.yml
  create  config/boot.rb
  create  config/database.yml
  create  db
  create  db/seeds.rb
  create  doc
  create  doc/README_FOR_APP
  create  lib
  create  lib/tasks
  create  lib/tasks/.gitkeep
  create  log
  create  log/server.log
  create  log/production.log
  create  log/development.log
  create  log/test.log
  create  public
  create  public/404.html
  create  public/422.html
  create  public/500.html
  create  public/favicon.ico
  create  public/index.html
  create  public/robots.txt
  create  public/images
  create  public/images/rails.png
  create  public/stylesheets
  create  public/stylesheets/.gitkeep
  create  public/javascripts
  create  public/javascripts/application.js
  create  public/javascripts/controls.js
  create  public/javascripts/dragdrop.js
  create  public/javascripts/effects.js
  create  public/javascripts/prototype.js
  create  public/javascripts/rails.js
  create  script
  create  script/rails
  create  test
  create  test/fixtures
  create  test/functional
  create  test/integration
  create  test/performance/browsing_test.rb
  create  test/test_helper.rb
  create  test/unit
  create  tmp
  create  tmp/sessions
  create  tmp/sockets
  create  tmp/cache
  create  tmp/pids
  create  vendor/plugins
  create  vendor/plugins/.gitkeep
</code></pre>

<p>$ rails s
```</p>

<p>As you can see the structure of a Rails project consists of quite a
few folders and files. This is a bit intimidating at first, but
becomes quite valuable once you&rsquo;ve used to the predefined
structure. You&rsquo;ll find a good overview of the structure <a href="http://ruby.railstutorial.org/book/ruby-on-rails-tutorial#sec:the_first_application">here</a>.</p>

<p>Open your browser and type
<a href="http://localhost:3000">http://localhost:3000</a> as the url. If
everything is OK you&rsquo;ll see a Rails welcome page.</p>

<p>At this point you should probably either start playing with
scaffolding or read the rest of this article and start playing with
scaffolding afterwards :&ndash;) For instance you can try:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ rails g scaffold User first_name:string last_name:string email:string password:string
$ rake db:migrate
$ rails s
</code></p>

<p>Open your browser and type
<a href="http://localhost/users:3000">http://localhost:3000</a> as the
url. &ldquo;Magic&rdquo; like this made Rails famous originally.</p>

<p>By default Rails apps use SQLite as a database backend, so might have
to install it as well.</p>

<p>The rails script is useful for various tasks &ndash; code generation,
plug-in installation, running a rails console, running a development
web server, etc.</p>

<h2>Django</h2>

<h4>Linux</h4>

<p>I prefer to install django from the distribution&rsquo;s package manager. On
a Red Hat distro like Fedora I would do:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo yum install Django
</code></p>

<p>And on a Debian system:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ sudo apt-get install python-django
</code></p>

<p>A popular alternative (that would work for OSX and Windows users as
well) to this distro-specific approach is to use a
python package manager like <a href="http://packages.python.org/distribute/easy_install.html">easy_install</a> or <a href="http://pypi.python.org/pypi/pip">pip</a>.</p>

<h4>Windows</h4>

<p>The <a href="http://bitnami.org/stack/djangostack">Bitnami Django stack</a> is the simplest way to get Django and
everything that it requires in a single step.</p>

<h4>Your first app</h4>

<p><code>bash
$ django-admin startproject djangodemo
$ ll djangodemo
total 16
-rw-r--r-- 1 bozhidar bozhidar    0 Jun 19 09:45 __init__.py
-rwxr-xr-x 1 bozhidar bozhidar  503 Jun 19 09:45 manage.py*
-rw-r--r-- 1 bozhidar bozhidar 5039 Jun 19 09:45 settings.py
-rw-r--r-- 1 bozhidar bozhidar  577 Jun 19 09:45 urls.py
$ cd djangodemo
$ ./manage.py runserver
</code></p>

<p>Compared to Rails, Django created a much simpler project
structure. There are only four files in here and only two are actual
Django configuration files &ndash; settings.py and urls.py. manage.py is
just a script useful for managing some aspects of the project (similar
to the rails script) &ndash; it can sync the model with the database, run a
development web server, run a django console, etc.</p>

<p>To test the new project open
<a href="http://127.0.0.1:8000/">http://127.0.0.1:8000/</a> in your browser.</p>

<h2>Features at a glance</h2>

<h3>Rails</h3>

<h4>Convention over configuration</h4>

<p>The centerpiece of Rails&rsquo;s philosophy is called convention over
configuration(CoC). This basically means that a Rails project has a
predefined layout and sensible defaults. All components (models,
views, controllers, layouts, css, javascript, etc) have standard
places where you should drop them and the application picks them up without
any additional effort on your part.</p>

<p>People seem to underestimate the importance of CoC in practice
initially &ndash; it
makes it a lot easier to reason about a project and a lot easier to
configure the project. On the other hand if some of the defaults don&rsquo;t
work for you &ndash; you&rsquo;d have to jump through some hoops. Recent versions
of Rails, however, have made it a lot easier to tweak the defaults.</p>

<p>All in all I feel that CoC is a big win for developers and I guess
many people share my opinion since CoC can now be found in many other
frameworks as well.</p>

<h4>MVC to the bone</h4>

<p>Rails is a classical Model-View-Controller full stack web framework &ndash;
it handle all aspects of a typical web application. What separates it
from most of the MVC frameworks around is the heavy emphasis on
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Representational_State_Transfer">REST</a>. The
domain objects are treated as resources and could be handled in a
uniform manner using just the standard HTTP verbs like GET, PUT,
DELETE, POST. REST is extremely good fit for data driven applications.</p>

<p>As usual the model houses the application&rsquo;s business logic, the
controller invokes functionality from the model layer and feeds the
resulting data to the view layer, which display the data in a
meaningful way to the user.</p>

<p>The model layer is the home of your domain objects and the business
logic surrounding them. Domain objects (a.k.a. entities) are mapped to
database tables (at least in RDBMS). Unlike most object relational
mappers Rails&rsquo;s ActiveRecord (the default ORM; could be substituted
with something else if you wish) doesn&rsquo;t require you to explicitly
declare the structure of the objects, but rather extracts it
automatically from your DB table definitions. A simple class, modeling
an application user might look like this:</p>

<p><code>bash
class User &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  validates :first_name, :last_name, :email, :password, :presence =&gt; true
  validates :password, confirmation: true
end
</code></p>

<p>Note that the validation methods are entirely optional (but highly
recommended) &ndash; the class could have very well had an empty body. Rails
would know to look for a table named Users in the database and extract
the field information from it.</p>

<p>Rails generates automatically for us &ldquo;finders&rdquo; that we can use to make
queries about objects in pure Ruby. It also provides an elegant DSL to
express relationships between various model classes (belongs_to,
has_many, etc)</p>

<p>In the view layer Rails has traditionally relied on HTML templates
with Ruby code embedded in them (html.erb). There are a lot of
community contributed alternatives, however, with HAML being the most
prominent one. On a similar note Rails allows you to use SASS as a
replacement for traditional CSS.</p>

<p>Another centerpiece in Rails is the &ldquo;Don&rsquo;t Repeat Yourself&rdquo;(DRY)
principle. In the view layer partial templates, layouts and helpers
are some of the tools available to help you abide by that
principle. You&rsquo;ll certainly make heavy use of them in your
applications so you should pay them some special attention.</p>

<h4>Database migrations</h4>

<p>Everyone that has done some serious programming knows that it&rsquo;s not
realistic to presume that the initial database schema won&rsquo;t ever
change &ndash; fields get added/removed, new tables get introduced,
etc. All those changes are commonly referred to as &ldquo;migrations&rdquo; and
traditionally every team unrolls its own handling of the problem. On
my last job I was tasked at some point to write a tool in Java that
analyzed a config file and a directory structure filled with SQL
scripts and applied them selectively to various target databases. In
Rails you get this functionally for free &ndash; you can express your
migrations as simple Ruby scripts and you can use rake to generate the
appropriate SQL statements for any supported database. Here&rsquo;s a simple
migration script, that creates the Users table:</p>

<p>``` ruby
class CreateUsers &lt; ActiveRecord::Migration
  def self.up</p>

<pre><code>create_table :users do |t|
  t.string :first_name
  t.string :last_name
  t.string :email
  t.string :password

  t.timestamps
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def self.down</p>

<pre><code>drop_table :users
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>The up method gets invoked when the migration is applied and the down
method gets invoked when it&rsquo;s reverted. Rails 3.1 will offer even more
elegant migrations. To execute all migrations:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ rake db:migrate
</code></p>

<h4>Ajax from within</h4>

<p>Rails features tight integration with JavaScript and AJAX. Versions
prior to 3.1 shipped by default the prototype and scriptaculous
JavaScript libraries. In
version 3.1 jQuery will replace them as the default JavaScript
library.</p>

<p>Making and handling AJAX requests in Rails is generally very easy &ndash; a
big advantage in today world ruled by rich and dynamic web UIs.</p>

<h4>Extensibility</h4>

<p>Rails is extendable through a multitude of community supplied plugins
that could add incredible functionality to your apps for free. Some of
my favorite plugins are <a href="https://github.com/indirect/jquery-rails">jQuery for Rails</a>,
<a href="https://github.com/bcardarella/client_side_validations">client side validations</a> and <a href="https://github.com/sferik/rails_admin">Rails Admin</a>.</p>

<h4>Testing is not optional</h4>

<p>What I particularly like about Rails is that it heavily promotes
testing your code. All of the Rails generators would generate test
stubs, that you&rsquo;ll do good to fill in. Rails supports all major Ruby test
frameworks &ndash; Test::Unit, RSpec, Cucumber. You have fixtures support, test
database support, the ability to run unit and functional test
separately. I don&rsquo;t recall using any other framework that pays as much
attention to having tests as Rails and for that I can only
congratulate the Rails team.</p>

<h4>Compatibility with Ruby versions</h4>

<p>There are two major version of Ruby out there presently &ndash; Ruby 1.8.7
and Ruby 1.9.2. Ruby 1.9.2 offers substantial language and performance
improvements, so you should be pleased to hear that Rails supports
both major Ruby versions. Rails 4.0 will drop support for Ruby 1.8.x.</p>

<p>Rails can also be run on top of JRuby and Rubinius.</p>

<h4>Deployment options</h4>

<p>The most common deployment options for Rails are currently Apache
HTTPD or NginX and Phusion Passenger (mod_rails). People shopping for
cloud Rails deployment should definitely take a look at Heroku.</p>

<p>Rails also runs on alternative Ruby implementations like JRuby and
Rubinius (as mentioned above), that offer exciting new possibilities. For instance using
JRuby allows you to deploy a Rails app into a Java application server
like JBoss or Glassfish and to tap into all those great Java libraries
and frameworks around. Using JRuby also gives you the opportunity to
deploy your apps on Google&rsquo;s App Engine.</p>

<h3>Django</h3>

<h4>A simpler project layout</h4>

<p>While I had some experience with Rails from a couple of years ago,
Django was something totally new to me. I expected it to be more or
less Rails for Python, but when I created my first Django app I was
surprised to see that the project folder consisted of only three
files (I&rsquo;m obviously not counting the python package file
<strong>init</strong>.py).</p>

<p>My initial surprise aside it turned out that most differences were
just superficial and that Django and Rails have quite a lot of
similarities. I&rsquo;ll, however, speak a bit more about the different
stuff than the similar stuff.</p>

<h4>MVC(MTV), Django style</h4>

<p>While Django is a MVC controller framework as well, it&rsquo;s built around a
different mindset. Django is totally configurable and minimalistic
framework that empowers the developers to tailor it to their needs.</p>

<p>A Django project is comprised of autonomous and reusable apps. Apps on
the other hand are comprised of models, views and templates. Django
differs a bit in terminology with Rails &ndash; the Rails controllers are
views in Django and the Rails views are called templates in Django. You
can sometimes hear that Django is a Model-Template-View framework &ndash;
that shouldn&rsquo;t confuse you. Although the terminology is different the
principles are the same.</p>

<p>Django&rsquo;s default ORM is somewhat reminiscent of frameworks like
Hibernate. Entity classes declare explicitly the all the
attributes. Let&rsquo;s consider again the User model class:</p>

<p>``` python
from django.db import models</p>

<p>class User(models.Model):</p>

<pre><code>first_name = models.CharField(max_length=30)
last_name = models.CharField(max_length=30)
email = models.EmailField()
password = models.CharField(max_length=30)
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Both approaches have their strengths and weaknesses an usual. In
Django&rsquo;s case we have increased verbosity, but on the other had we
don&rsquo;t have to inquire the database to figure out the exact definition
of model records.</p>

<p>Like in Rails we get useful &ldquo;finders&rdquo; that can be used to query for model
objects in pure python (as opposed to using sql).</p>

<h4>In the template layer</h4>

<p>While ERB is basically HTML with Ruby embedded in it, Django features
a custom templating language with it&rsquo;s own (extendable) tag
library. This generally means that Django templates tend to be a bit
cleaner than Rails&rsquo;s templates, since you&rsquo;re not allowed to abuse them
very much. On the other hand you can do virtually anything by
embedding code directly in a template, so as usual &ndash; each design
decision has its pros and cons.</p>

<p>Django supports alternative templating libraries, so you&rsquo;re covered in
case you don&rsquo;t like the default one.</p>

<p>Django also features a powerful form generation/handling facilities
that integrate seamlessly with the templating layer. For instance &ndash; it
very easy to generate a form matching the structure of a domain model
object with automatic property validation.</p>

<h4>You&rsquo;re in charge</h4>

<p>Django has doesn&rsquo;t adhere to the Rails CoC philosophy. It&rsquo;s assumed
that developers know best what layout and configurations options make
the most sense in their applications. I haven&rsquo;t played that much with
Django yet, but I still haven&rsquo;t come by two different Django apps that
are structured in the same manner. While I understand the benefits of
Django&rsquo;s approach I still prefer Rails&rsquo;s approach. I&rsquo;ve worked long
enough to know that you&rsquo;re rarely in the position to make better
decisions about the structure and the defaults of your app, than the
exceptional developers with huge experience that develop frameworks
like Rails and Django.</p>

<p>To illustrate this consider the strong emphasis Rails places on
REST. In Django you could certainly use restful access your resources
as well, but it&rsquo;s all up to you. The framework makes no
suggestions. You can unroll any URL mapping scheme by simply
associating regular expressions in urls.py with callback view
functions:</p>

<p><div>
  <pre><code class='python'>from django.conf.urls.defaults import patterns, include, url&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;urlpatterns = patterns(&amp;lsquo;&amp;rsquo;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;url(r&#39;^$&#39;, &#39;djangodemo.views.home&#39;, name=&#39;home&#39;)
url(r&#39;^users&#39;, &#39;djangodemo.view.users&#39;, name=&#39;list_users&#39;))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</code></pre>
</div>
</p>

<p>An url is mapped to the callback function, which in turn either renders a
template or directly returns some Http response.</p>

<h4>Free admin</h4>

<p>Django has a built-in support to generate an admin UI for your
website. This is a very useful feature indeed and is supported in
Rails as well through plugins (I&rsquo;ve mentioned the one I like the
best).</p>

<h4>Database migrations</h4>

<p>One of the few gripes I have with stock Django is that it doesn&rsquo;t
offer an alternative to Rails&rsquo;s migrations. Luckily there is
<a href="http://south.aeracode.org/">South</a> &ndash; an extension that provides a
simple, stable and database-independent migration layer to prevent all
the hassle schema changes over time bring to your Django
applications. I highly recommend it to everyone planning to use
Django.</p>

<h4>JavaScript and AJAX</h4>

<p>Unlike Rails, Django doesn&rsquo;t bundle any JavaScript libraries. You have
to pick a JavaScript framework yourself (which a trivial process). The
AJAX support in Django is both basic and extremely powerful in the
same time &ndash; request.is_ajax(). What this means is that you can check
if a request was regular or an AJAX request and respond
accordingly. You don&rsquo;t need much more than that. More details can be
found <a href="https://code.djangoproject.com/wiki/AJAX">here</a>.</p>

<h4>The great divide</h4>

<p>Some of you probably know that Python is currently at a bit of a
crossroads. Python 2.x was the stable Python version for many years,
but recently it was replaced by Python 3.x. Python 3.x is all around
great in my personal opinion, but unfortunately it&rsquo;s backward
incompatible with the older 2.x series. For that reason very few high
profile projects still don&rsquo;t support it &ndash; Django is one such
project. The current version 1.3 require at least Python 2.4 and will
run with every Python up to 2.7. This is a bit of a disappointment
since you&rsquo;ll be missing on a few very cool new features. On a more
positive note Python 2.7 did backport some goodies from Python 3, so
not all is lost. I&rsquo;ve read (at totally unofficial places) that Django 2.0 will be targeting Python 3
and I expect it will be available in about a year.</p>

<h4>Deployment</h4>

<p>Python is quite mature technology and offers you a nice array of
deployment options &ndash; Apache, Nginx and my favorite &ndash; Google App
Engine. Python, being one of the two supported languages on the App
Engine (the other one is, of course, Java) makes it very easy to deploy
Django apps on the App Engine (though you&rsquo;ll need the Django support
for non-relational databases to be able to use it).</p>

<p>The also the possibility to deploy Django apps on Java or .Net
infrastructure using Jython or IronPython.</p>

<h2>Community</h2>

<p>When you&rsquo;re selecting the technology for a major project you have to
make sure that the technology is in good shape &ndash; there is a solid
community around it, there is no lack of support, innovation and
deployment options.</p>

<p>Both
<a href="http://www.google.com/trends?q=ruby+on+rails%2C+django+python">Google trends</a>
and stackoverflow.com (by the number of question about tagged with
django or rails) indicate that Rails currently has larger
community than Django.</p>

<p>I haven&rsquo;t had any direct communication with the Django community yet,
but I&rsquo;ve found a lot of excellent resources about Django on-line.</p>

<p>Rails has one of the most vibrant, passionate and innovative
communities. I&rsquo;ve had contact with a lot of people from the Rails
community and I&rsquo;m certain that it has played a tremendous role in
Rails&rsquo;s growth.</p>

<h2>Tooling</h2>

<p>Traditionally Ruby &amp; Python hackers have been working with just a
powerful programmer&rsquo;s editor like Emacs, vim or TextMate. While there
is nothing inherently wrong with this approach (I&rsquo;m an avid Emacs user
myself), I do find IDEs quite helpful when working on larger code
bases, with their trademark features such as intelligent
autocompletion (aka intellisense), safe refactorings, on-the-fly syntax checking, etc. So
here&rsquo;s what we&rsquo;ve got:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/ruby/">RubyMine</a> &ndash; hands down the best Ruby and Rails IDE I&rsquo;ve ever
used. The <a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/ruby/features/index.html">list of features</a> is epic as is the quality of the
project. It support Rails 3, git, RSpec, Cucumber, sass, haml and
many other cool Ruby/Rails related technologies. Sure, it&rsquo;s a
commercial project, but is priced very reasonably.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.aptana.com/">Aptana Studio</a> &ndash; a Web development IDE,
built on top of the Eclipse platform. Among many other features it
supports Ruby on Rails.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.activestate.com/komodo-ide">Komodo</a> &ndash; an IDE focusing on
dynamic programming language. Great support for both Django and
Rails development.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/pycharm/">PyCharm</a> &ndash; from the same company that develops RubyMine, PyCharm
is the king of IDEs when it comes down to Python. It has full
featured Django support &ndash; there is even autocompletion in the Django
templates.</li>
<li><a href="http://pydev.org/">PyDev</a> &ndash; an Eclipse plug-in for Python and Django development.</li>
</ul>


<p>I have to admit I&rsquo;m totally biased. Having been a long time Java
developer I&rsquo;ve grown extremely fond of the exceptional IntelliJ
IDEA. RubyMine and PyCharm are both based on the IntelliJ platform and
bring to the Ruby and Python developers much of the might and magic of
IDEA. There are both commercial products, but their price tags are
quite low and their quality is great &ndash; highly recommended.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not affiliated in any way with any of these products &ndash; I just
happen to like them that much.</p>

<h2>Resources</h2>

<p>The are LOTS of resources about Rails and Django on-line. Here are
just my favorites.</p>

<h4>Rails</h4>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://guides.rubyonrails.org/">Rails Guides</a> &ndash; best short
introduction to Rails ever. Immediately updated for new Rails
versions, fantastic starting point for any aspiring Rails developer.</li>
<li><a href="http://ruby.railstutorial.org/">Rails Tutorial</a> &ndash; best Rails 3 book
on the market and it even has a free on-line edition. Nice follow up
of the Rails Guides.</li>
<li><a href="http://railscasts.com/">RailsCasts</a> &ndash; Ryan Bates in true Ruby
hero. He has compiled a unique set of high quality Rails screencasts
that often illustrate some advanced techniques. And they are all
free. We all owe a very big &ldquo;Thanks!&rdquo; to Ryan.</li>
</ul>


<h4>Django</h4>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/1.3/">Official Docs</a> &ndash; best
official project documentation I&rsquo;ve read. It&rsquo;s actually so good,
that I never (well &ndash; almost never) bothered to look for anything else. All my questions
were answered by the official documentation.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Epilogue</h2>

<p>Choosing Django or Rails is basically a win-win situation &ndash; you cannot
go wrong. There are too many similarities between the frameworks and
the differences are not something paramount.</p>

<p>Rails places a heavy emphasis on convention over configuration,
provides you with more defaults and does a can do a lot of heavy
lifting for you automagically.</p>

<p>Django on the other hand let&rsquo;s you specify most configuration details
yourself, without making the configuration burdensome (like that of
older Java web frameworks).</p>

<p>Rails has always been leading on the way of innovation &ndash; constantly
integration some of the latest and greatest technologies around
(recent examples being jQuery, Coffee Script and SASS). From time to
time backward compatibility is sacrificed for the greater good, so
that is something that you should consider as well.</p>

<p>Django is certainly much more conservative framework as far as
backward compatibility is concerned &ndash; after all it still support
Python 2.4.</p>

<p>I guess in the end the choice really boils down to two things &ndash; whether you
like Ruby or Python better and whether you like the defaults imposed
to you by Rails.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve planned to write a much longer and detailed article, but it&rsquo;s
summer here and it&rsquo;s sunday and I&rsquo;d rather go out and drink a few
beers with my friends. Hopefully you&rsquo;ve enjoyed the article. I&rsquo;ll try
to expand it a bit in the coming days.</p>

<p>P.S. Btw, in case you&rsquo;re wondering &ndash; we&rsquo;ve picked Rails for our
company&rsquo;s projects. It was a very close call, though, since I
really liked a lot of aspects of Django as well.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ruby or Python? Well, it depends...]]></title>
    <link href="http://batsov.com/articles/2011/05/03/ruby-or-python/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-03T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://batsov.com/articles/2011/05/03/ruby-or-python</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong></p>

<p><em>If you&rsquo;re looking for a flame post &ndash; this is not one of them. I love
both languages and I&rsquo;ll simply compare some of their features and
possible uses.</em></p>

<h2>Prelude</h2>

<p>Ruby or Python? This is the Question! Well it might not be the
Question, but it&rsquo;s a common question for many developers looking to
break free from the statically typed language they know and learn a
dynamic language. I personally know them both(though I know a bit more
Ruby, than Python) and in this article I&rsquo;ll share my personal opinion
on their strengths and weaknesses. You&rsquo;d probably do good to learn
them both, but my arguments here may lead you to pick only one of the
languages depending on you preferences.</p>

<h2>Installation</h2>

<p><strong>Linux/Unix installation</strong></p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re using a Linux distribution or some other Unix derivative
such as *BSD or Solaris you&rsquo;ll probably be able to install Ruby and
Python through the operating system&rsquo;s software management system. For
instance on Debian Linux systems(Ubuntu is a popular Debian
derivative) you can use apt to install them. Run the following
commands as root or with sudo:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ apt-get install ruby
$ apt-get install python
</code></p>

<p>On Red Hat based distros like Fedora, CentOS, etc you can use yum
instead:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ yum install ruby
$ yum install python
</code></p>

<p>You should keep in mind the fact that both Ruby and Python have two
version that are commonly used at the moment. Ruby&rsquo;s current version
is <em>1.9.2</em> and Python&rsquo;s is <em>3.2</em>. For various reasons(like backward
compatibility for instance), however, the current versions are not
widely deployed yet(especially Python 3). In most Linux distributions
the package ruby will actually be Ruby 1.8.x and the package python
will be Python 2.7.x. If your distribution is one of those &ndash; look for
packages named ruby19(or similar) and python3:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ apt-get install ruby19
$ apt-get install python3
</code></p>

<p>or on a Red Hat system:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ yum install ruby19
$ yum install python3
</code></p>

<p>Using the distribution package management system is a simple solution,
but in the case of Ruby it might not be best one. Most Ruby hackers
favour a powerful bash script called RVM(Ruby Version Manager) that
allows you to install several different version(or flavours of Ruby)
and switch easily between them. Please refer to the official
<a href="https://rvm.beginrescueend.com/">RVM documentation</a> for installation
and usage instructions.</p>

<p><strong>Windows installation</strong></p>

<p>Installing Ruby on Windows used to be a pretty hard task, but this is
no longer the case now thanks to
<a href="http://rubyinstaller.org/">the RubyInstaller for Windows</a>. This is a
self-contained Windows-based installer that includes the Ruby
language, an execution environment, important documentation, and
more. It has two editions one for the older 1.8.x Ruby branch and one
for the current 1.9.x.</p>

<p>Python has several installation options for Windows &ndash; the most obvious
being the
<a href="http://python.org/ftp/python/3.2/python-3.2.msi">official Python installer for Windows</a>. <a href="http://www.activestate.com/activepython">ActiveState&rsquo;s ActivePython</a>
is another popular option packed with more features, but you should
keep in mind that although the Community Edition is free ActivePython
is not an open-source project. Personally I prefer ActivePython. Other
prebuilt Python binaries for Windows are also available, but are not
commonly used.</p>

<p><strong>OS X installation</strong></p>

<p>Ruby is generally preinstalled on OSX, but OSX users can also install
it via <a href="http://mxcl.github.com/homebrew/">homebrew</a> or RVM(as mentioned in the Linux section).</p>

<p>The is an official <a href="http://python.org/ftp/python/3.2/python-3.2-macosx10.6.dmg">Python package for OSX</a> available. Most users
will probably prefer using homebrew, however.</p>

<h2>Syntax &amp; code structure</h2>

<p>Ruby makes heavy use of braces and keywords(like do/then/end) to
delimit blocks of code. Python relies simply on indentation.</p>

<p>``` python
def fact(n):</p>

<pre><code>return reduce(lambda x, y: x * y, range(1, n + 1))
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Same thing in Ruby:</p>

<p><code>ruby
def fact(n)
  (1..n).reduce(:*)
end
</code></p>

<p>I personally prefer the Python approach since it enforces the code
semantics based on the code structure alone without imposing special
syntax.</p>

<p>As a side node you might take under consideration that the Ruby method
definition doesn&rsquo;t have an explicit return value. The value of the
last expression in the method&rsquo;s body becomes automatically the
method&rsquo;s return value. Lisp developers will find this familiar. Java
and C# developers will probably find it a bit confusing. There is a
<code>return</code> in Ruby, though, it&rsquo;s just rarely used.</p>

<p>Both languages have support for nested function definitions.</p>

<p>Both languages have support for &ldquo;top-level&rdquo; functions &ndash; that live(or
seem to live) outside classes and modules(something not possible in
Java for instance). This makes them good for general purpose
scripting. While I would still prefer to do my system administration
with shell and Perl scripts &ndash; Ruby and Python offer a solid
alternative. Python has a richer system administration library so I&rsquo;d
prefer it over Ruby for such tasks.</p>

<p>Ruby has a lot of crust(&ldquo;heritage&rdquo;) from Perl &ndash; like a myriad of
special variables that are now more or less deprecated. It also has
much syntactic sugar &ndash; for instance do/end is commonly replaced by {}
for blocks that are only one line long, there is special syntax for
hashtables, whose keys are symbols, etc.</p>

<p>Since special symbols(non alphanumeric) are allowed in Ruby
identifiers Ruby uses them to impose some naming conventions to make
the source code a bit more readable in certain scenarios &ndash; for
instance predicate methods(those that return true or false) have names
that end with ?(usually) like even?, odd?, prime?, etc. Methods that
mutate the object on which they were invoked generally have the !
suffix &ndash; sort!, map!, etc. I find this a nice decision. In Ruby you
generally have many ways to achieve the same result:</p>

<p><code>irb
ruby-1.9.2-p0 &gt; 1.even?
 =&gt; false
ruby-1.9.2-p0 &gt; arr = [1, 2, 3]
 =&gt; [1, 2, 3]
ruby-1.9.2-p0 &gt; arr.map { |x| x * 2 }
 =&gt; [2, 4, 6]
ruby-1.9.2-p0 &gt; arr
 =&gt; [1, 2, 3]
ruby-1.9.2-p0 &gt; arr.map! { |x| x * 2 }
 =&gt; [2, 4, 6]
ruby-1.9.2-p0 &gt; arr
 =&gt; [2, 4, 6]
ruby-1.9.2-p0 &gt; (1..5).reduce(:*)
 =&gt; 120
ruby-1.9.2-p0 &gt; (1..5).reduce { |x, y| x * y }
 =&gt; 120
ruby-1.9.2-p0 &gt; (1..5).reduce do |x, y|
ruby-1.9.2-p0 &gt;     x * y
ruby-1.9.2-p0 ?&gt;  end
 =&gt; 120
</code></p>

<p>No such things in Python, however. Python&rsquo;s philosophy is one of
simplicity &ndash; no excessive syntax sugar, one true way of doing things.</p>

<p>Both languages have powerful features for organising code in
libraries. I would not go into any details on the subject here, but
I&rsquo;ll share with you the fact that I like Python&rsquo;s more.</p>

<p>Both languages come with a REPL in which you can do some exploratory
programming. Ruby&rsquo;s REPL(irb)  allows you
to do TAB smart completion(amongst other things) by default. To get
TAB completion in the Python REPL you&rsquo;d have to execute this bit of
code first:</p>

<p>``` pycon</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>import readline, rlcompleter
readline.parse_and_bind(&ldquo;tab: complete&rdquo;)
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>Alternative you can just stick this code snippet in the
<strong>~/.pythonrc.py</strong> file(create it if it doesn&rsquo;t exist). If you are using
Windows adjust accordingly(you will have to figure out where
pythonrc.py is located there).</p>

<p>Ruby does not have statements &ndash; only expressions. This
basically means that everything(objects, method calls) evaluate to
some value(though the value might not be helpful always).</p>

<p>In Python there are some statements such as assignment and <em>if</em>. One
thing I dislike about the Python REPL is that it doesn&rsquo;t print None
values. Compare this bit of Python code:</p>

<p>``` pycon</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>print(&ldquo;this is a test&rdquo;)
this is a test
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>to this Ruby snippet:</p>

<p><code>irb
ruby-1.9.2-p0 &gt; puts "this is a test"
this is a test
 =&gt; nil
</code></p>

<p>In the Python version we see only the side-effect(the printing), but
not the return value.</p>

<p>Python also ships with a minimalistic IDE called IDLE. If you don&rsquo;t
have it by default after a python installation on Linux probably
you&rsquo;re vendor decided to package IDLE as a separate package. IDLE
offers basic features like syntax highlighting, code completion and
integration with a debugger. It&rsquo;s a good tool for exploratory
programming, but I advise you to pick another tool for serious development.</p>

<h2>Naming conventions</h2>

<p>The naming conventions for both Ruby and Python are mostly the same
which is good if you&rsquo;re using them both on a daily basis &ndash; less room
for confusion.</p>

<ul>
<li>variable and method names consisting of more then one word are
written in lowercase with underscores separating the individual
words like_this.</li>
<li>Class names start with capital letter and follow the camel case
naming convention LikeThis. Some of Python&rsquo;s core classes, however,
violate this convention.</li>
<li>Constants are generally written in all caps with underscores
separating the individual words LIKE_THIS.</li>
</ul>


<p>As I mentioned earlier it&rsquo;s customary to add ? as a suffix to
predicate methods and ! to mutator methods in Ruby. This convention is
not always followed unfortunately, even in Ruby&rsquo;s standard library.</p>

<h2>OOP support</h2>

<p>Both Ruby and Python are famous members of the family of object
oriented languages. Unlike languages such as Java and C#, however,
Ruby and Python are pure OOP languages. There is no distinction
between primitive types(such as numbers, characters and booleans) and
reference types(classes). Everything in them is an object and in that
sense it&rsquo;s an instance of some class:</p>

<p>``` pycon</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>type(1)
<type 'int'>
type(&ldquo;string&rdquo;)
<type 'str'>
type(20.07)
<type 'float'>
type([1, 2, 3])
<type 'list'>
type((1, 2, 3))
<type 'tuple'>
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>And in Ruby:</p>

<p><code>irb
ruby-1.9.2-p0 &gt; 10.class
 =&gt; Fixnum
ruby-1.9.2-p0 &gt; "string".class
 =&gt; String
ruby-1.9.2-p0 &gt; [].class
 =&gt; Array
</code></p>

<p>As you can see core Ruby classes tend to have a bit more standard and
descriptive names than their Python counterparts. You can also notice
that in Python for some task we use built-in functions like type,
instead of method calls. The built-in function will eventually result
in a method invocation(like &ldquo;string&rdquo;.<strong>class</strong> in the case of
type(&ldquo;string&rdquo;)), but I find this irregularity in the syntax a bit
irritating.</p>

<p>Method invocation is more flexible in Ruby &ndash; you can omit braces in
some scenarios. This is handy when you&rsquo;re designing a DSL or you&rsquo;re
trying to implement the uniform access patterns(data should be
accessed through fields and methods in the same manner(read this as
with no braces in method invocations)). On the other hand Python&rsquo;s
uniform syntax makes it easier to spot method invocations.</p>

<p>Both languages don&rsquo;t have operators &ndash; just methods. Ruby&rsquo;s OO support
seems to be a bit more mature and polished(at least to me), but
Python&rsquo;s has some touches as well. I particularly like the explicit
self references that are required when you try to access class
members. I&rsquo;m not too found of the use of special sigils in Ruby to
mark instance(@) and class members(@@). Though they make them visually
distinctive I think we could have lived without them &ndash; I&rsquo;m generally
not a fan of non-uniform syntax rules(and you guessed it &ndash; my
favourite language is Lisp).</p>

<p>Ruby&rsquo;s metaprogramming model arguably gives it an edge in the OOP
department, but I won&rsquo;t be discussing the metaprogramming issues here
since they are quite lengthy.</p>

<h2>Functional programming support</h2>

<p>Functional programming has been on the rise lately and it&rsquo;s useful to
examine what kind of support both languages provide for it. Both have
support for lambda functions and respectively &ndash; higher-order
functions(functions that accept functions as parameters). Ruby has
code blocks, Python has list comprehensions(generally favoured over
higher-order functions). Both languages lack in their standard libs
the immutable data structures that generally are the code of most
functional programming languages. Here&rsquo;s a few example related to
filtering a sequence based on some predicate:</p>

<p>``` pycon</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>filter(lambda x: x % 2 == 0, range(1, 11))
[2, 4, 6, 8, 10]
[x for x in range(1, 11) if x % 2 == 0]
[2, 4, 6, 8, 10]
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>Ruby:</p>

<p><code>irb
ruby-1.9.2-p0 &gt; (1..10).select { |x| x.even? }
 =&gt; [2, 4, 6, 8, 10]
ruby-1.9.2-p0 &gt; (1..10).select &amp;:even?
 =&gt; [2, 4, 6, 8, 10]
</code></p>

<p>Ruby&rsquo;s functional programming support seems to be better to me, but
this is of course subjective.</p>

<h2>GUI programming</h2>

<p>Python has tkinker by default &ndash; a wrapper around the Tk library(which
sucks in my humble opinion). Ruby doesn&rsquo;t have even this much. Both
have binding for the popular GUI toolkits such wxwidgets, GTK,
QT. From my experimentation with them I can tell you that you&rsquo;ll be
much better off with Python in that department. It&rsquo;s not wonder that
many GTK+ applications these days are implemented in Python. Most Ruby
bindings projects seem to be in a state of disarray, abandonment &ndash; I
guess we have to thank Rails for that. Most people think of Rails as
the only use of Ruby which is sad&hellip;</p>

<p>Ruby devs shouldn&rsquo;t despair however. JRuby(Ruby&rsquo;s port to the JVM) has
an excellent support for the superb Swing GUI framework and MacRuby
has great support for building Cocoa Apps for OS X. I personally think
that JRuby is the best Ruby distribution out there, but that&rsquo;s the
point of another post entirely.</p>

<h2>3rd party library availability and installation</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s not secret that part of Python&rsquo;s philosophy is that it comes with
batteries included &ndash; meaning that it&rsquo;s standard library is vast and
covers a lot of common tasks. In case you can&rsquo;t find what you&rsquo;re
looking for in it you&rsquo;re left with an number of third party libraries
for Python whose number can only be described by the word epic and
that cover every task conceivable. <a href="http://pypi.python.org/pypi">PyPi</a>
maintains an up-to-date list of Python packages.</p>

<p>You have several options in the department of python package
management. If you&rsquo;re using ActivePython you can use the excellent
<a href="http://code.activestate.com/pypm/">PyPM</a> tool, which provides quick
installation of thousands of packages for many Python versions and
platforms for ActivePython distributions.</p>

<p><a href="http://peak.telecommunity.com/DevCenter/EasyInstall">EasyInstall</a> is another popular solution that works with the standard
Python distribution. Like PyPM it allows you easily search for and
install Python packages from the PyPI that are bundled in Python&rsquo;s
standard egg format(Jave developers might think of eggs as
jars). EasyInstall has splendid documentation so I won&rsquo;t go into any
details here.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.pip-installer.org/en/latest/index.html">pip</a> is a
replacement for easy_install. It uses mostly the same techniques for
finding packages, so packages that were made easy_installable should
be pip-installable as well.</p>

<p>pip is meant to improve on EasyInstall. Some of the improvements:</p>

<ul>
<li>All packages are downloaded before installation. Partially-completed installation doesn’t occur as a result.</li>
<li>Care is taken to present useful output on the console.</li>
<li>The reasons for actions are kept track of. For instance, if a package is being installed, pip keeps track of why that package was required.</li>
<li>Error messages should be useful.</li>
<li>The code is relatively concise and cohesive, making it easier to use programmatically.</li>
<li>Packages don’t have to be installed as egg archives, they can be installed flat (while keeping the egg metadata).</li>
<li>Native support for other version control systems (Git, Mercurial and Bazaar)</li>
<li>Uninstallation of packages.</li>
<li>Simple to define fixed sets of requirements and reliably reproduce a set of packages.</li>
</ul>


<p>pip doesn’t do everything that easy_install does. Specifically:</p>

<ul>
<li>It cannot install from eggs. It only installs from source. (In the future it would be good if it could install binaries from Windows .exe or .msi – binary install on other platforms is not a priority.)</li>
<li>It doesn’t understand Setuptools extras (like package[test]). This should be added eventually.</li>
<li>It is incompatible with some packages that extensively customize distutils or setuptools in their setup.py files.</li>
</ul>


<p>Linux users will also find a great selection of Python libraries
prepackaged for use with the distribution&rsquo;s package manager.</p>

<p>Ruby has an application that is more or less equivalent to EasyInstall
called <a href="http://rubygems.org/">RubyGems</a>(gems are the standard way to distribute Ruby
libraries). Linux users can of course install Ruby libraries with the
distribution&rsquo;s package manager as well.</p>

<p>RubyGems has the following features:</p>

<ul>
<li>Easy Installation and removal of RubyGems packages and their dependents.</li>
<li>Management and control of local packages</li>
<li>Package dependency management</li>
<li>Query, search and list local and remote packages</li>
<li>Multiple version support for installed packages</li>
<li>Web-based interface to view the documentation for your installed gems</li>
<li>Easy to use interface for building gem packages</li>
<li>Simple server for distributing your own gem packages</li>
<li>Easy to use building and publishing of gem packages</li>
</ul>


<p>Using RubyGems, you can:</p>

<ul>
<li>download and install Ruby libraries easily</li>
<li>not worry about libraries A and B depending on different versions of library C</li>
<li>easily remove libraries you no longer use</li>
<li>have power and control over your Ruby platform!</li>
</ul>


<p>A reader pointed out that about 23000 packages are available for
installation through RubyGems and 15000 through PyPI. This, however,
cannot be considered as a certain sign that there are more libraries
available for Ruby than for Python.</p>

<p>Although tools like EasyInstall and RubyGems are easy to use and quite
handy, I as a long-time Linux users dislike them a bit, since they
circumvent the distributions native package handling. Unfortunately
package maintainers cannot find the time to package every Python and
Ruby library available so I guess EasyInstall and RubyGems won&rsquo;t be
going anywhere soon and of course we have to consider Windows users
for whom such applications are of great value given the lack of
unified package management on Windows.</p>

<p>One thing to keep in mind about installing eggs and gems is that some
of them are implemented in C(usually for performance reasons) and are
locally built prior to their installation &ndash; an operation bound to fail
if you don&rsquo;t have a C compiler installed.</p>

<h2>Misc</h2>

<p>In terms of performance of the default interpreters CPython and MRI
Ruby Python is the clear winner. One should note, however, is that there
are many how quality implementation of Ruby and Python for different
platforms where the performance situation differs wildly. For instance
Jython is much slower that JRuby. With the addition of invoke_dynamic
in JDK7(basically bytecode level support for dynamic method dispatch)
the performance of JRuby and Jython could potentially be improved
greatly.</p>

<p>In terms of overall usage, market share, job offers and sheer size of
the community and available libraries Python is ahead of Ruby as
well. One of the main supporters of Python is after all none other
than the mighty Google. Ruby has also the unfortunate luck to be
living in the shadow of a single application written in Ruby &ndash; Ruby on
Rails, that is arguably more popular than the language itself.</p>

<p>Tooling for dynamic languages is currently not as advance as the one
for static languages. People often joke that Python(Ruby) > Java(C#),
but Python + any python IDE &lt; Java + IntelliJ
IDEA(Eclipse/NetBeans). Python and Ruby IDEs seem to be mostly on par
currently. I do all of my Ruby and Python coding in Emacs, but I do
like RubyMine and PyCharm.</p>

<p>Since they are often used for the creation of webapps one should
consider the deployment issue. Most web hosting companies provide
cheap Python hosting, but very few companies provide Ruby hosting.</p>

<h2>The Python 3 problem</h2>

<p>Python 3 was a great undertaking that improved on a lot of aspects of
the language(for example Unicode support) and the standard library. To
do this it dropped backward compatibility, an act that slowed it&rsquo;s
adoption immensely. Three years have passed since it&rsquo;s release and
still most hosting providers, Linux distros and Python projects hold
on to the older 2.7.x Python branch.</p>

<p>This is a bit of tragedy since Python 3 is truly a great improvement
over Python 2. I mention this because most recent books are written
with Python 3 in mind, but if you land a Python jobs somewhere chances
are you&rsquo;ll have to use Python 2.x.x for the foreseeable future.</p>

<h2>Epilogue</h2>

<p>Ruby and Python are two beautifully engineered languages capable of
just about everything. If you don&rsquo;t know any of them you&rsquo;ll do well to
learn at least one. If you know only one it might not be a terrible
idea to learn the other.</p>

<p>I haven&rsquo;t touched on many language features(like Python generators and
Ruby mixins), but to be honest I&rsquo;m just tired of typing. One good
place to start your journey to Python is
<a href="http://diveintopython3.org/">&ldquo;Dive into Python 3&rdquo;</a>. For Ruby
beginners I&rsquo;d recommend a copy of
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Ruby-Programming-Language-David-Flanagan/dp/0596516177">&ldquo;The Ruby Programming Language&rdquo;</a>.</p>

<p><em>P.S. If you like exploring different programming languages and you&rsquo;re
currently shopping for ideas on the subject of which language to learn
next you might find my recent article
<a href="/blog/2011/04/27/programming-languages-worth-learning/">&ldquo;Programming languages worth learning&rdquo;</a>
interesting as well.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
